<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some necessary disquisitions and close expostulations with the clergy and people of the Church of England, touching their present loyalty written by a Protestant.</title>
            <author>Protestant.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2319</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12016460</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12016460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 878:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some necessary disquisitions and close expostulations with the clergy and people of the Church of England, touching their present loyalty written by a Protestant.</title>
                  <author>Protestant.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Smith :</publisher>
                  <publisher>and are to be sold by R. Fenarray ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52535:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52535:1"/>
            <p>Some Neceſſary DISQUISITIONS AND CLOSE EXPOSTULATIONS WITH THE <hi>Clergy and People</hi> OF THE CHURCH OF ENGLAND, Touching their preſent LOYALTY.</p>
            <p>Written by a Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to the Citizens of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>F. Smith,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Jenaway,</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52535:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52535:2"/>
            <head>To the Honoured and Worthy Gentlemen, the Citizens and Inhabitants of the moſt Eminent and Famous City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe <hi>Papers</hi> are directed to you, in regard your City hath been the chiefeſt <hi>Scene</hi> of many of thoſe things, which their deſign is for the future to prevent. I do not direct them to you as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in your Body Politick, but to each man by himſelf (that may happen to look on them) in his indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Capacity. And having ſaid this, I think it proper in the next place to give you ſome account of the Reaſons that chiefly induced me to this undertaking, which you may briefly take, in what follows.</p>
            <p>I was for ſeveral Years a very <hi>unpleaſant</hi> Spectator of the proceedings of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> towards thoſe her Diſſenters, that could not Worſhip <hi>God</hi> with their <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> Which as I did <hi>deeply</hi> diſlike, ſo I would fain have excuſed her, and laid the blame if I could ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe, (as themſelves it ſeems now would do.) But I found it impoſſible to ſatisfie my reaſon in that Attempt, while I daily met with, and heard of ſuch <hi>inveterate</hi> Sermons, againſt that <hi>Rank</hi> of Perſons, aswere then Preached by the moſt Capital Men of the Function, and <hi>as the Old Cocks crew,</hi> ſo did the <hi>young Ones</hi> learn, who are not to be exempted from acting their part in the <hi>Clamour;</hi> divers of them being no ſooner allow'd to tread the Stairs of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> but with their little Declamations that way, were quickly as loud as the beſt of their Doctors.</p>
            <p>Had the Supreme Civil <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> or his <hi>Subordinates,</hi> dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on thoſe Proſecutions, while the Clergy had interpoſed
<pb facs="tcp:52535:3"/>with their Chriſtian perſwaſions to the contrary, it would have gone very far towards the leſſening the Complaint; but when the Civil Magiſtrates ſhall draw back, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſhall Spur forward, I know not who in this caſe can be the Clergies Advocate.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall ſay no more of this; only entreat you to look back, and conſider how exceeding uneaſie all things that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to your Station (as Citizens) were made to you. Do you not remember what commotions, inquietudes, ſtrange and unfriendly Diviſions, were all that time among you, and how one Neighbour was put upon deſtroying another, and every Man in fear of himſelf, and jealous of whomſoever he ſpoke to?</p>
            <p>Do you not likewiſe remember what huge Interruptions many of you met with in your dealings with your Country <hi>Shop-keepers,</hi> Traders and Manufacturers, even to a great ſtop of your wonted <hi>Traffick?</hi> And (as other bad effects theſe proceedings had upon your City) what a Stand moſt Men were at, who had let out their Moneys at <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or Lodged them with the <hi>Gold-Smith</hi>-Lankers, or the <hi>Chamber</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don?</hi> While divers of them thereupon conceived thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfactions, as cauſed the calling in ſo much of thoſe Monies, in ſo ſuddain a manner, as to beget that Inſolvency, which diſappointed the future ſettlement of many of the Sons and Daughters of your ſellow Citizens. A thing perhaps would make your Hearts <hi>Bleed,</hi> ſhould you ſee the like Mis-fortunes happen to your own <hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Bleſſed</hi> be <hi>God,</hi> the State of Affairs are now much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by his <hi>Majeſties</hi> late Declaration, taking away the <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> of theſe Diſtractions, inſomuch as there ſeems to me to be the beginning of a General happy Settlement, while I ſee Men of different perſwaſions in Religion, that before ſtood at a diſtance each from the other now, amicably to intermix and <hi>unite</hi> in their Trade, Correſpondencies, and Buſineſs; yea, and in the publick Government both of the City and
<pb facs="tcp:52535:3"/>the Kingdom, from whence it is already perceived, that the difference of opinion, in Religion, hinders nothing from an unanimous agreement of all Perſons, managing thoſe Truſts in a due <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the King, and for the general good and peace of the Kingdom, while one party is not ſet to oppreſs the other in his Religion.</p>
            <p>Nor need any Man to doubt, but ſuch a good beginning would ſoon grow up to an abſolute <hi>Perfection,</hi> did not ſome Men (who have little reaſon more than the Gratifying their own <hi>Jealouſies</hi>) make the oppoſition. For what Foundation can be better laid for the <hi>Flouriſhing</hi> State of any Kingdom, then that aſſurance His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath given in the two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of his <hi>Declaration,</hi> which he would have to be Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in a more perpetual <hi>Law, viz.</hi> That the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Government ſhall fully be with ſuch Juſtice, as every Man ſhall be preſerved in his <hi>Temporal</hi> property. And in Spiritual concernments as to Worſhipping of <hi>God,</hi> ſhall have his free Liberty. Which two things being <hi>firmly</hi> ſetled; from whence can it be imagined, any pretence ſhould be found for the worſt of Spirits, to ſet on Foot any Diſturbances, Plots, or Inſurrections? He that now ſhould but ſo much as offer at any ſuch thing, will preſently fall under that general Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt with all Engliſh Men, as they will think him to deſerve no leſs puniſhment, than to be preſently <hi>Hung</hi> up by the <hi>Heels,</hi> until he Spew out his <hi>Gall</hi> and Die.</p>
            <p>Who they are that make the oppoſition I ſpeak of, and by what means they manage it, you will find in the Book it ſelf: I ſhall only ſay here, that it is by ſome of thoſe that heretofore have carried all the <hi>Crack</hi> for <hi>Loyalty;</hi> and this is the true cauſe that hath drawn theſe Diſquiſitions and Expoſtulations from me; that ſo I may know how they can make what they do of this kind conſiſtent, with their <hi>preſent</hi> Loyalty: In order to which you will meet with a neceſſary queſtion, put to them for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Matters of Fact on which I often touch, and upon
<pb facs="tcp:52535:4"/>which a great part of my Diſcourſe doth proceed; having been many of them done within the Lines and Limits of your Liberties. I have thought no other Perſons ſitter to be made <hi>Arbitrators</hi> in them (as they are here Controverted) than your Selves.</p>
            <p>And that there may be no miſtakes, or needleſs Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the preſent caſe, I have plainly laid down my own No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Loyalty:</hi> wherein I have thought the Nature of it more <hi>eſpecially</hi> to conſiſt, That ſo if any Perſon hath a mind to appear againſt what I have Written, I do firſt pray him to contradict me in thoſe <hi>Notions,</hi> and then he will recover me from my firſt Error: or if he finds he cannot do that, I ſhall then pray him to ſhew me my <hi>bad Arguings</hi> from ſuch good Principles, and that will recover me from my ſecond Error, (if, of any ſuch Error I ſhould be guilty) and this is the Method I intreat any ſuch Perſon to take, that may ſo concern himſelf.</p>
            <p>I have been a Man who have always thought, that there was much more in the <hi>Duty</hi> of Loyalty, than to Write or Preach againſt <hi>Rebellion;</hi> or cry up the Doctrine of a meer external <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> always believing, that Men may be guilty of high <hi>Diſloyal</hi> Acts even to the introducing of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion) while themſelves declare they abhor it. This I learn'd from the Writing of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Page</hi> 18.30.</note> as you will meet with in its place.</p>
            <p>If any think I have written more favourably of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion, than becomes a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> I muſt reply to him, I have written nothing at all, either for or againſt one way of <hi>Religion or</hi> other, but rather Refer (as I ſaid juſt now) to ſuch matters of Fact, relating to the Three perſwaſions of the R. <hi>Catholicks:</hi> The <hi>Church of England,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> as were neceſſary to carry on what I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and if in doing ſo, and in comparing ſome things or practices of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> I find that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath upon its <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:52535:4"/>Principles, made <hi>Laws</hi> for the puniſhing her Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diſſenters (producing as bad Effects, as thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) and thereupon ſay that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants Sufferings from the Church of the <hi>England,</hi> were in their <hi>Extent</hi> harder upon them, ſince the laſt Settlement of their Uniformity, than they can be ſaid to have been under Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> it doth not follow from hence, that I Write for her Religion, but rather that I am one that deſire to Write impartially.</p>
            <p>Or if while I ſee the Church of <hi>England</hi> Miniſters, either in their Printed Books, or Sermons, expoſing as they have done of late, ſome Doctrines or Practices of the other Church, more to a Popular Contempt, than for an Edifying Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the People, as they formerly dealt by the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and take occaſion from thence to ſhew them in ſome particulars, how very many of their own Practices and Doctrines, may be in the ſame manner expoſed. I hope I may not be the worſt Proteſtant for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>If I reverence that Divine Principle, <hi>viz. That Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the matter of Gods Worſhip is not o the forced,</hi> I am not to be blamed, until I be otherwiſe convinced; no, nor if I Write againſt thoſe who oppoſe His Majeſty in ſettling the Kingdom (upon that Principle) in a Freedom from thoſe Diſtractions, which the practices of many upon the contrary Principles, have ever ſince the Reformation brought upon it. The principle is ſuch as I cannot but <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue</hi> and <hi>love</hi> with all my <hi>Heart,</hi> becauſe I know it to be ſo agreeable to the Sence of every Mans mind, That no Man, who knows what belongs to the Sincere worſhipping of God, dare allow himſelf to be unwilling in any part of his Life, to live otherwiſe than under its Benefit, when I am otherwiſe convinced I may recal much of what I have Written; but until then I am like to go on in the ſame way I am in.</p>
            <p>If my Stile or way of writing be offenſive to you, as any
<pb facs="tcp:52535:5"/>whit too ſharp, I muſt crave your remiſſion of that (if you judge it to be a fault and for my excuſe, muſt ſay, I unhappily learn'd it from the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> chiefeſt Doctors. He that ſhall Read their Controverſal Books and Sermons, as I have done, written againſt the Roman Catholicks and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters, will tell you it is next to an impoſſibility, not to imbibe the Faculty of their way of Writing.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I have no more to ſay here, but wiſh your Citty, all imaginable happineſs, and each of your Selves and Families; the Bleſſings of this <hi>World,</hi> and that which is to <hi>come.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52535:5"/>
            <head>Some neceſſary Diſquiſitions, and Cloſe EXPOSTULATIONS WITH THE <hi>Clergy and People</hi> OF THE <hi>Church of England,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HOW highly the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath valued Her Self, both upon the account of Her Loyalty, and the ſuper excellency of Her Conſtitution and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, is ſo well known among us, as no Man needs my telling him any thing about it. This is that Her Preachers and Members have ſo much boaſted of; as if in the point of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty they were the only choice Perſons in all his Majeſties Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and in the caſe of Church Excellency, they were the beſt and pureſt of all Churches in the World.</p>
            <p>If all this were true, it is pity they ſhould have ever done any thing, that might in the leaſt wiſe loſe or darken the Glory of ſuch Excellencies; or to make any Perſons think otherwiſe of them, than they think of themſelves: But I am in great doubt, that if the People of <hi>England</hi> were divided into four Parts, more then three of the four would be found to be of another Mind; not only as to the excelling goodneſs of their Church, but from ſome things they have lately done, as to their Loyalty too. In the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52535:6"/>former it is apparent, for why elſe have ſuch a Multitude of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent and well diſpoſed Perſons (as to Religion) with-drawn themſelves from Her? chooſing father to bear all ſorts of Afflictions then to be held in its Communion. Not only a great number of Catholicks (for ſo we commonly in compliance with their own phraſe, call thoſe who hold to the Religion of the Chruch of <hi>Rome</hi>) but even among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> alſo, far greater numbers are found Zealous <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from <hi>Her,</hi> which ſurely muſt be from ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they both of them find to give them great Diſſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>And as to their Loyalty, I could likewiſe with that they had given no occaſion to conſiderate Men to find as much defect in that as the other; being ſuch as in many Mens Opinions hath drawn upon it ſo great a Blemiſh, as will not eaſily be wiped <hi>off;</hi> eſpecially while they cannot but take notice of <hi>two things.</hi> The one is, for ſo many of Her Clergy Mens Vehement Preaching againſt the Kings Religion. The other is, of the Irreverent Speeches and Cenſures many of Her Members have been found to expreſs againſt His late <hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt acknowledge, they have had the Advantages heretofore of tendring their Loyalty very ſpecious; when as all the Kings after the Reformation were wholly of their Perſwaſion, and yielded themſelves very much to be led by them, but now when we have a King from whoſe Religion they conſiderably differ, their Loyalty ſeems to be like that of thoſe Mens which they formerly Condemned. I do not ſay they take up Arms, but as ſome Men have ordered the matter, they have done that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves which heretofore did in others too much lead the way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch bad practiſes.</p>
            <p>When I firſt obſerved that ſtrain of Preaching, in which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them run, immediately upon his Majeſties coming to his Throne; I muſt confeſs my ſelf amazed at it, for I ſaw him no ſooner proclaimed <hi>King,</hi> but all on a ſudden we had ſuch <hi>ratling Sermons,</hi> both in City and Country againſt his <hi>Religion,</hi> as if the Preachers had ſeen in a Viſion that the Religion of <hi>Rome</hi> had been to be ſet up here in the firſt Month of his <hi>Reign.</hi> Their hearers alſo, and among them ſome of the <hi>chiefeſt ranck</hi> as to external quality (too much influenced it may be, by ſuch kind of Preaching) have not been wanting to expreſs themſelves at the ſame rate of <hi>Ill Reflections</hi> againſt his <hi>Declaration;</hi> touching which I have heard ſuch hard Speeches as I could not poſſibly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52535:6"/>have thought could have ever come from Perſons in Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with that Church. To be plain and ſhort, they have not only in the general ſuggeſted that there would be an Alteration in the <hi>National Religion;</hi> but they ſtick not to ſay, that the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Liberty</hi> granted for the free Worſhipping of God, is purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to introduce Popery; and contemptuouſly compare the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty granted by the Declaration to a <hi>Scaffold,</hi> ſet up for that intent which muſt be ſo much the worſe ſaid of them, as that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration it ſelf aſſures them the Protection of their own Religion as it is now Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not Expatiate on the Occaſions, Grounds, and Methods, of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reformation, either in Doctrinals or Diſcipline; but only obſerve, that after ſome beginnings in K. <hi>H. 8ths</hi> time, and further progreſs made under K. E. 6th all turned Retrograde by Q. <hi>Mary.</hi> In the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> things were brought again to ſome ſeeming Conſiſtency; and <hi>then,</hi> that which we now term the Church of <hi>England</hi> by a Sanction of State, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived its full Eſtabiſhtment.</p>
            <p>The Conſtitution and Nature of which Church is now become to be an <hi>Independent National Hierarchy, of Arch Biſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Arch-Decons, Prebendarys,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe chief Worſhip was at firſt made to be with a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> but ſuch an one as wherein it was in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with no other Church upon the face of the Earth; tho by this time, there were divers other Proteſtant Churches in being: Yet was this ſet up and ſetled with as much abſoluteneſs, as if it had been all indited by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or our <hi>Saviour</hi> Himſelf. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Worſhip, whoſoever came not, or abſented by the ſpace of a Month, was to be puniſhed in the forfeiture of twenty pounds ſucceſſively for every Month ſo offending. This was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> for the ſupport of the Reformation; after which others were made more ſevere, eſpecially, againſt thoſe who were in Church <hi>Orders</hi> of the Catholick Religion, for Death was to be inflicted upon any of them that were but ſo much as found to be within the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>This Reformation had not long continued before divers Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants themſelves began to find it faulty; it was much wondred on all hands, when it was obſerved, how all was pretended to be done in it according to the <hi>Rule</hi> of the Scripture, while that <hi>Rule</hi> and their whole conſtitution did ſo much diſagree. That they ſhould keep up among themſelves a Superiority of Paſtors, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52535:7"/>reject the having one to be <hi>univerſal.</hi> That they ſhould with great violence inforce a few Ceremonies ſingled out for ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known uſe, and yet caſt off others (uſed in the Church from whence they reformed) no leſs inviting and <hi>ſignificant;</hi> There were alſo great Exceptions againſt their <hi>Liturgy,</hi> the R. Catholicks complain'd, that tho' indeed it was taken almoſt all out of their <hi>Service,</hi> yet, it was ſo mingled and mangled as that they had made it utterly defective to the ends of a compleat rule of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for them to joyn with. Many Proteſtants who liked well enough to ſee a Reformation begun, yet thought the firſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers went but half way; but above all other things it was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſliked, that ſuch <hi>new things</hi> and ſo different from all others Churches ſhould be ſo ſeverely impoſed.</p>
            <p>Theſe things (as <hi>Cambden</hi> writes) preſently bred great diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>'Tis incredible</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>what Controverſies and Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aroſe upon this,</hi> which he ſpeaks in relation to Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> time, and the new impoſitions that followed the firſt Setle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the proſecutions to inforce that uniformity; for he gives us an Account how about the Year 1583. Biſhop <hi>Witgift</hi> who was advanced from the See of <hi>Worceſter</hi> to that of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> propounded to the Miniſters three new <hi>Articles</hi> for their Subſcribing, which ſet on foot thoſe differences. But more to my purpoſe, is the Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burleghs</hi> Letter to the Arch-Biſhop himſelf upon theſe Commotions, dated <hi>July</hi> 5th, 1584. Wherein he complains of the Arch Biſhops proceeding, and the ill effects thy were like to have upon the <hi>Queens</hi> Safety.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Grace (ſaith he) <hi>I am ſorry to trouble you ſo often as I do, but I am more troubled my ſelf:</hi> not only with many private <hi>Petitions of Sundry Miniſters recommended from Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Credit for peaceable Perſons (yet greatly troubled) but alſo I am dayly now charged by Councellors, and publick Perſons to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect my Duty in not ſtaying theſe your Graces proceedings ſo Vehement and ſo General againſt Miniſters, and Preachers, as thereby evil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Perſons are animated, and the Queens Majeſty endangered.</hi> It ſeems from hence that this has been an Old Trade among our Epiſcopal Clergy; firſt, to make very uncouth Impoſitions, and then perplex peaceable Miniſters that cannot Conſcienciouſly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them. And a little while after he tells His <hi>Grace</hi> again, how theſe proceedings were <hi>rather a device to ſeek for offenders, than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any:</hi> I wiſh we had not as much occaſion to ſay the ſame
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52535:7"/>thing now in reference to ſome of our late Contrivances, as this grate <hi>State Man</hi> did then; however, from the premiſes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion may be fairly made, how unſutable a thing it appears to have been then judged for the Reformation, to think to ſettle it ſelf and its Princes in peace by ſuch Methods.</p>
            <p>Nor did theſe Diſtractions ceaſe with the Death of that Queen, for though the Non-conformiſts might not have been dealt with ſo ſeverely upon Kings <hi>James</hi> the firſts coming to the Crown (in regard the manner of the Church of <hi>Scotlands</hi> worſhip differed much from the Liturgy and Ceremonies of <hi>England,</hi> by which means things might continue in the more quietneſs and peace for a while) yet in ſome competent time, the Clergy who were always working both with him and King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, to keep the Reigns of their Church Diſcipline as ſtrait and hard upon them as may be, prevail'd much upon both thoſe Kings to countenance them in divers of their new injunctions, until all things broke our into a moſt woful Confuſion.</p>
            <p>I know the Church of <hi>England</hi> are unwilling to own, that the rigorous Impoſing and Proſecuting their new <hi>Articles, Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions,</hi> brought on the War in 1641. but thoſe that will give themſelves the trouble to look into the Printed Speeches ſtill remaining with us, ſpoke then in the Houſe of Commons, may there be ſatisfied how they improved were to bring an Odium up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kings Government, and inflame the Spirits of the People into a <hi>War,</hi> which ever ſince may juſtly be called <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What deplorable miſeries this War produced to the <hi>Royal</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firſt, to the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> next; yea, and to the <hi>Clergy</hi> themſelves at laſt. How their Liturgy was trod under foot, their Biſhops and whole Hierarchie rooted up, their Church Lands ſold, and a ſecond Reformation proclaimed to correct the firſt, are all things freſh in Memory to thoſe who are ſtill living and ſaw them, and all the world has wondered how the Church of <hi>England</hi> did ſo ſoon forget them, as it appears She did; for She was no ſooner out of the Fiery Furnance of her Afflictions by the Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d, but down right ſhe falls upon her old pollicies of effecting an uniformity by vertue of <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> when they had ſeen before the event of them in their Predecſtors, to have given them ſo much diſcredit; and when they might have ſufficiently learned how impoſſible it is upon Proteſtants Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, to erect and enforce a National uniformity in Religion to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52535:8"/>any one way of Worſhip; but that there would ſtill be Diſſenters who upon their <hi>own</hi> Principles may plead an Exemption from it.</p>
            <p>However, they reſolved to make a ſecond Experiment, and once more to try if they could make the whole People in <hi>England</hi> to be in their Religion all of one <hi>Complexion;</hi> to which purpoſe a new Act of Uniformity is made, more ſtrict than that which went before, with a new <hi>Teſt</hi> of <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; for bare <hi>Conformity</hi> in the uſe of the Liturgy will not now do, there muſt be <hi>Swearing</hi> alſo: All other waies of Religious publick Worſhip are made <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and the Act of 20 <hi>l.</hi> a Month for not coming to Church revived; and tho' it was alwaies thought to have been made directly againſt R. Catholicks, it muſt now be made a ſharp Scourge equally to all <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Confuſions and Troubles theſe things brought upon His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects, may be underſtood ſomething from thoſe who have given a publick Account of them, a Printed Catalogue has informed us of neer 2000 Miniſters turned out of their Livings by the Uniformity Act, which was ſoon followed by another made at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that turned them alſo out of their Houſes to ſeek their Bread where they were no wiſe like to find it. Another who was well able to make the Eſtimation, informs us of fifteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Families ruined by the <hi>Conventicle Act,</hi> by proceedings againſt their Eſtates, and Impriſonment of their Perſons; among whom (he ſaies) five thouſand dyed under their bonds: And if we ſuppoſe but three Children a peice to belong to thoſe Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies one with another, we muſt compute no leſs than forty five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſufferers in their <hi>Eſtates</hi> by theſe <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> for if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents be ruined, their Children cannot but be deep <hi>Sufferers</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>Do we talk of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies, as times of ſharp Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Alas! they were little to this, Doctor <hi>Burnet</hi> gives an account but of 284. that ſuffered death in Her time, and what is this to 5000. that have dyed under this Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor doth he ſay any thing of looſing their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> or the Childrens being deprived of what their Parents had. I know a great matter is made by puniſhing Perſons with <hi>Death;</hi> but for my part I ſee little difference between ſuffering by the preſent Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Death,</hi> and being ſtifled or ſtarved to <hi>Death</hi> by the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and hardſhips of a Priſon, and ſuppoſing it lawful to make ſuch a choice in caſe I muſt neceſſarily ſuffer by one of the two; I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52535:8"/>ſhould chooſe to ſuffer by the former rather then by the latter, and I know many more to be of my mind.</p>
            <p>How thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> can defend Her, from being the only procuring cauſe of all theſe Miſeries to thoſe Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of afflicted Perſons and Families. I can no waies apprehend, let them that can do it, begin their Work as ſoon as they pleaſe; in the mean time I hope they will not be angry, if I endeavour to ſhew them how much all their proceedings this way was againſt the mind of King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond; who all along endeavoured to put a ſtop to their Severities, from the deſires he had that his Subjects might have injoyed the Liberties in Religion which they now do; and this before he came into <hi>England,</hi> as well as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſo ſoon as he ſaw what work was like to be made by the Execution of thoſe Laws they had got him to <hi>ſign,</hi> choſing other more pious and peaceable Methods for his Subjects Eaſe. Let us hear ſome of his own Words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> April 4th, 1660. gives the firſt aſſurance of this. <hi>We declare a Liberty to tender Conſciences, and that no Man ſhall be diſquieted or called in queſtion for differences in Opinion, which do not diſturb the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi> Then again <hi>Feb.</hi> 10th. 1667. <hi>Speaking to the Parliament one thing</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>I hold my ſelf obliged to recommend to you, at this preſent; which is, that you would ſeriouſly think of ſome courſe to beget a better <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Compoſure in the Minds of my Proteſtant Subjects in matters of Religion,</hi> &amp;c. Which undoubtedly muſt be intended towards the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation of the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> for in his Declaration, <hi>March</hi> 5th. 1671. He complains again of the ſeverities then in uſe, ſaying, <hi>That it was evident by the ſad experience of</hi> 12 <hi>years, that there was little fruit of all thoſe forcible courſes, and many frequent waies of Co-ertion that we have uſed for the reducing of all erring and diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons.</hi> Again, in his Speech to both Houſes of Parliament, 1678. <hi>I meet you here with the moſt earneſt deſire, that a Man can have to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite the Minds of my Subjects, both to me and one another, and reſolve it ſhould be your fault if the ſucceſs be not ſutable to my deſires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus for neer twenty years together, was this King labouring againſt the Violences of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> towards thoſe his Subjects whoſe Worſhipping of God differed from <hi>theirs;</hi> and who were the Men, but themſelves that then oppoſed Him in it? And at whoſe door but <hi>theirs</hi> muſt all theſe deplorable Calamities
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52535:9"/>be laid, that have happened by the want of that Indulgence, that King would have given, and is now granted by his Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Succeſſor, they may if they pleaſe conſider it more fully at their Leiſure.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty that now is, by a Gracious and moſt Wiſe <hi>Retroſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> upon all that had been Tranſacted in theſe Affairs, during the four laſt Kings Reigns; and from a <hi>God-like</hi> compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Oppreſſed Subjects, in the midſt of their Calamities, ſends out his moſt refreſhing <hi>Declaration,</hi> ſuſpending the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all thoſe <hi>Penal Statutes,</hi> that had been but very little before ſo fiercely Executed. Upon this, many thouſands of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, Diſſenters, of all perſwaſions through out the Kingdom (who had been formerly by the Church of <hi>England</hi> repreſented to the <hi>late King,</hi> as a ſort of Humourſome, Fanatical, Diſobedient Perſons, and Enemies to Monarchy, and every thing elſe that looked that way) come in with their <hi>Humble Acknowledgments.</hi> Firſt, of Gods goodneſs to them, as believing ſuch a publick Mercy, could not be but by immediate his guidance of the Kings Heart in the thing; after this they declare their <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Thanks</hi> to His Majeſty, as far as Honeſt and Dutiful Words can expreſs, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring him of their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and Prayers for his long and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Reign.</p>
            <p>They humbly tell Him alſo, that to his <hi>Three</hi> Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> he hath now eſtabliſhed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a <hi>fourth</hi> Kingdom in the Hearts of thoſe his formerly oppreſſed Subjects, which as I believe to be true; ſo was it modeſtly ſpoken inaſmuch as the Diſſenters are known to be, far exceeding the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a <hi>fourth</hi> part of the People of the <hi>three</hi> Kingdoms. Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others teſtify their joy, in that ſo good an opportunity is given them to expreſs the truth of their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which the Church of <hi>England</hi> had hitherto preſumed to have been entailed wholly on themſelves. A great many engage to <hi>Live</hi> and <hi>Die</hi> with him, to the utmoſt of their lives and fortunes. But paſſing by all others, I would eſpecially mark thoſe who in the Capacity of a <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> thank the King for his <hi>Declaration</hi> as it has preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted honeſt Neighbours from <hi>indicting one another in the things of Religion,</hi> which to many Conſciencious Men was a very great burthen; and to the whole Kingdom a greater vexation then I can now ſtand to ſpeak of, begiting ill will, and irreconſitable dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between one and the other of his Majeſties Subjects; which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52535:9"/>being by this means now taken away, it is hoped their old Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency will be henceforth renewed in a true love of each Man to his Neighbour.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of this happy Union, between His Majeſty and his Diſſenting Proteſtant Subjects, the Church of <hi>England</hi> like the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Elder Brother, mentioned by our Saviour in the Parable of the <hi>Prodigal,</hi> ſtand at a diſtance and Grumble: They will neither thank their <hi>Princely</hi> Parent for the Favour He vouchſafeth to themſelves, nor will they come in to rejoyce with their <hi>Younger Brethren</hi> upon their Dutiful return, and the Kings kind reception of them; a thing ſo much the more culpable ſince none of the <hi>fatted Calfs</hi> (I mean the <hi>Church Revenues</hi>) are in the leaſt killed for them, but are as they were before wholly in the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> own Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>'Tis almoſt beyond rehearſals, the diſlike they ſhew of this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> as if they delighted to keep up the ſame, or raiſe other and worſe Confuſions, during his preſent Majeſties Reign, as they begot in the time of his <hi>four laſt Predeceſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bond of this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> which I may ſay, is His Majeſties Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Declaration,</hi> many of them can ſcarce hear named, but they are ready to fly back like Men that had trod on a <hi>Serpent:</hi> One ſhakes the <hi>Head,</hi> another bites the <hi>Lip,</hi> a third <hi>Scouls</hi> and <hi>Frowns;</hi> with as many other Evidences of their diſlike, as <hi>Bodily Geſtures</hi> can ſhew: And it would have been well, could they have contented themſelves within the Bounds of thoſe tacite Intimations of their diſpleaſure; but this they could not do, they muſt alſo break into <hi>Words</hi> and open <hi>Cenſures,</hi> ſuch as I have named before.</p>
            <p>I do not charge <hi>all</hi> with this, but I muſt ſay, I daily find and meet with an abundance too many that are ſo doing; inſomuch as I think it highly neceſſary for every Man in his place to put a Stop as far as he can, to the further progreſs of it. For my ſelf, I know no better way that I can take, then to mind them of the Inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſuch deportment with their boaſted of <hi>Loyalty;</hi> a thing of which they have ſeemed to be as tender, as of the <hi>Aple</hi> of their <hi>Eye.</hi> And if they are <hi>ſtill</hi> ſo ſerious therein, as they would be eſteemed, they ſhould as I conceive judge themſelves not a little concerned in a <hi>Queſtion</hi> I have here to propoſe to them, and the rather, becauſe, I undertake to maintain the <hi>Negative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The queſtion is plainly this, <hi>viz. Whether it be Conſiſtent with that high degree of</hi> Loyalty <hi>ſo much boaſted of by the Church of</hi> England, <hi>for their Preachers in the manner they have done to Preach againſt their Kings</hi> Religion, <hi>and both them and their Church Members to ſpeak as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52535:10"/>they too frequently, do againſt His Proceeding by his late Declaration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This queſtion is the bottom of all my following Expoſtulations, wherein that I may proceed with the more perſpecuity; I ſhall do no more then make inquiry into two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall examine wherein the higheſt degree of <hi>Loyalty</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſence of the Scriptures may be ſaid to conſiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall inquire how the preſent Behaviour of many of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both Clergy, and <hi>Layety</hi> agrees, with that <hi>Loyalty</hi> which I ſhall diſcribe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, I am guided by two Texts of Scripture, from whence I may argue as much as I ſhall need to my purpoſe, the one is that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13, 1, 2. <hi>Let every Soul be Subject to the higher Power,</hi> where <hi>Subjection</hi> is required to be given for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> which makes it become <hi>a Religious Act.</hi> To give Subjection <hi>only</hi> becauſe we cannot avoid it, or becauſe we are compelled, is the Subjection of an <hi>Infidel</hi> or a <hi>Turk</hi> rather than a Chriſtian. The oppoſite to this is Reſiſtance, which is twofold. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That which is by <hi>open Violence</hi> to the Perſon of him that is our Soveraign, or to his Subordinate Miniſters. The <hi>ſecond</hi> is, when we Diſobey or Speak againſt <hi>His Precepts, Edicts,</hi> or the <hi>Declaration</hi> of His <hi>Will,</hi> which be ſends forth in the Execution of His <hi>Government;</hi> for not to Submit, or to Speak againſt what he Directs is to <hi>reſiſt.</hi> So <hi>Luke</hi> 21.15. To <hi>gain-ſay</hi> and <hi>reſiſt</hi> are made the ſame thing; a Man may make reſiſtance as well by his <hi>Tongue,</hi> as his <hi>Sword,</hi> from whence I infer that one part of the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> is a cheerful and willing compliance with the <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red will</hi> of the King in all things, (without gain-ſaying) not contrary to the Law of God.</p>
            <p>The other Paſſage is that of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> where we are bid <hi>to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King.</hi> This is a degree much higher than a bare forbaring of <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> or diſputing his Commands; for a Man may give O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and be outwardly <hi>Silent</hi> towards Him, who in his Heart he <hi>Slighteth: To Honour the King,</hi> contains in it many Acts, both In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and External; our Internal <hi>Honouring</hi> Him lyeth chiefly in that reverential <hi>Eſteem</hi> we have of His Perſon, as he hath the ſtamp of Gods Authority on him, [the <hi>valuation</hi> we give to His Vertues; The Faith we have in his <hi>Words and Promiſes,</hi> the Acquieſſence of out Minds in the Adminiſtrations of His Government, and judging the <hi>Beſt</hi> of His Actions, the contrary, to theſe are <hi>Jealouſies, Prejudices,</hi> all <hi>bad wiſhes</hi> and <hi>evil ſurmiſings,</hi> and judging of His Actions in the worſt ſence.</p>
            <p>The External way of Honouring Him, conſiſts likewiſe of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52535:10"/>parts, as when we are in his <hi>Preſence,</hi> to uſe thoſe bodily Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures as may beſt and moſt decently expreſs our inward reverence and ſence of his <hi>Dignity;</hi> the giving him his <hi>Honourable Titles,</hi> To ſpeak <hi>Reverently</hi> of him in the hearing and preſence of <hi>others,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent what we can all others from doing the contrary, that, thereby thoſe we Converſe with, may <hi>Honour Him</hi> as we our ſelves do.</p>
            <p>And to come more cloſs to the preſent <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of the times, I muſt ſay, that I judge one great part of our <hi>Honouring</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> to conſiſt in Addreſſing our ſelves to him in waies of publick and greatful acknowledgment of what ſpecial ſavours we receive from him; for I cannot believe otherwiſe, but that our Honouring the King muſt bear a great ſimilitude to our Honouring of God; and if ſo, then I am ſure Addreſſing when we would Honor Him, muſt not be left out as often as he gives occaſion. For Men to talk of <hi>Loyalty</hi> where theſe things are wanting, is but to abuſe the King and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too. Theſe things I ſhall illuſtrate further by two Examples.</p>
            <p>When King <hi>Saul</hi> delired <hi>Samuel</hi> to Honor him, wherein did he place that Honor? was it not by ſomething the Prophet ſhould do, that was to ſupport his <hi>Credit</hi> among the People? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.30. <hi>Honor me now I pray thee; before the Elders of my People. Saul</hi> was to be laid aſide, and put out of the Government, and he knew as much, but it is like he thought it not convenient to his preſent Condition that the People ſhould know it, which they might have done in all likely hood, had <hi>Samuel</hi> denyed his Requeſt. But, what doth <hi>Samuel</hi> in the caſe? Doth he not readily and openly ſhew his complyance? <hi>So</hi> Samuel <hi>turned again after</hi> Saul, <hi>and</hi> Saul <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Lord,</hi> for that was the thing requeſted of <hi>Samuel,</hi> viz. that he would go with the King to Worſhip God, before the Elders of the People.</p>
            <p>I hope no body Imagins that I extend this example, ſo far as to oblige all Subjects to Worſhip as their King doth (what Religion ſoever he profeſſeth) it proves my Argument better another way, <hi>viz.</hi> As it is an inſtance of the Obligation that lyeth upon Men in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Office as <hi>Samuel</hi> was, to maintain the Kings Honor in as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick a manner as their Place and Station give them Oppertunity, and forbiding them doing any thing that may render him <hi>mean</hi> in the eyes of the People, though they be not ſatisfied in all the King doth. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> thus honoured the King when he knew that God had rejected him in the Government; how then ought we to act towards a King, who we all know God by moſt remarkable Deliverances hath ſet upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>The like we have in the inſtance of King <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> mentioned in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52535:11"/>the Book of <hi>Eſther;</hi> who, when he asked <hi>Haman,</hi> what ſhould be done to the <hi>Man</hi> the King delighteth <hi>to Honor?</hi> was thus directed, <hi>viz. Let there be put on him the Royal Apparel</hi> — <hi>and bring him on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back through the ſtreets of the City, and proclaim before him, Thus ſhall it be done to the Man whom the King delighteth to Honor.</hi> Wherein tho <hi>Haman</hi> miſtook the Perſon at whom the King aimed (as think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it had been <hi>himſelf</hi> (he did yet hit right in the Notion of the thing, how that honor the King intended was to be effected, and what other thing was it, that he directed? but ſuch an act as ſhould render that Perſon to be great and <hi>worthy</hi> in the <hi>eyes of the Peopl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the true Notion of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> as it may be conſidered in its higheſt degree. The queſtion will now come more eaſie to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, I ſee no need of explaining any of its <hi>Terms,</hi> thoſe upon which the whole ſtreſs of it depends, are only concerning the <hi>manner</hi> of many of their Miniſters <hi>Preaching,</hi> and of their, and the Peoples <hi>Speaking;</hi> for I am not going about to tie-up either the People or any ſort of Preachers from aſſerting the Religion they profeſs, but when it ſo falls out, that there is any difference between theirs and their Kings Religion; I would not have it done in any way not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with their <hi>Loyalty.</hi> Now what that <hi>manner</hi> and method is, which divers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have taken up in theſe things, (both by their Miniſters in Preaching, and by their People in Speaking about the Kings <hi>Declaration,</hi> and his late proceedings in thoſe affairs,) which I conceive to be very inconſieſtnt with thoſe high degrees of <hi>Loyalty</hi> they pretend to, and theſe Texts lay before us; I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the particulars following, and firſt of the Preaching.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When there is more Preaching this way than there ſeems to be <hi>need for;</hi> or the ſuppoſed danger of the People requires, which ſeems to be much our preſent caſe: For I can no waies underſtand what neceſſity there is, or hath been for all the Preaching we have had <hi>of late</hi> againſt the Catholick Doctrines. Surely, our Preachers muſt think the People to be in great Danger of their <hi>Faith;</hi> but then, how comes it about to be ſo? Have they ſo much neglected them all the time before, as that now when a R. Catholick King comes to the Crown, they muſt be all <hi>new taught?</hi> Or, what is the Ground of all this fear? For certainly, ſome moſt Lamentable Apprehenſions muſt have ſtruck even to their very Souls, or elſe, they who have ſtood ſo mightily upon their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> would not run upon ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, as now to make it be called in Queſtion.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, Men in a <hi>Panick fear</hi> may do ſtrange things, but then I muſt ſtill be asking them <hi>What is it they Fear?</hi> or, what is that which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52535:11"/>thus excites them unto this Preaching? Do they fear the People will all on a ſudden become R. <hi>Catholicks?</hi> By many Mens Sermons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome are apt to think ſo, and that theſe Methods of the <hi>Pulpit</hi> are taken up as the only means to prevent it; Well! but then, I would know again <hi>of whom</hi> it is, and of what rank of People are they moſt <hi>afraid?</hi> For to ſpeak my own thoughts Freely, this ſeems to me to be a <hi>needleſs</hi> fear, and more <hi>imaginary</hi> than <hi>real;</hi> and could I ſuppoſe that the imparting ſuch Obſervations as I have made of theſe things, would in any wiſe obviate our <hi>Church-Mens Fears</hi> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I would then particularize the Caſe as to the People, and ſay,</p>
            <p>The <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> I think need not be Doubted, for they are a People ſo <hi>Anti-ceremonial</hi> in their Worſhip; and ſo much againſt any kind of <hi>Liturgies,</hi> or impoſed <hi>Prayers,</hi> as that they upon that reaſon are many of them withdrawn from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore very unlikely to go to any <hi>Maſs.</hi> And among thoſe that go to the Pariſh <hi>Churches,</hi> there are divers Serious People who ſo approve of the <hi>Diſſenters Worſhip,</hi> as that they ſteal oftner to it than their Miniſters are aware of; and theſe may be ſuppoſed (upon the ſame reaſon) to be in as little danger as the other.</p>
            <p>There being then no great ground of fear for theſe, it muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that thoſe they are moſt <hi>afraid</hi> of, are ſuch as are of their <hi>own Church;</hi> and here the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> cannot refrain Smiling, to ſee that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath ſo fairly Coppied out Her <hi>Liturgy, Ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>Hierarchie</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they ſhould now be afraid <hi>their own</hi> People of all others ſhould like the <hi>Original</hi> better than the imperfect <hi>Copy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To come then to their own <hi>Church,</hi> are they the <hi>Gentry</hi> or the <hi>Commonalty?</hi> and among them, are they thoſe that are moſt <hi>intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> and <hi>ſincere,</hi> or thoſe who are more <hi>indifferent</hi> and <hi>remiſs</hi> in the true parts of practical <hi>Piety</hi> that have given them this <hi>Extraordinary</hi> fear? Which of theſe ranks of Perſons in their <hi>Church</hi> they aim at in theſe Preachings is to me unknown; though under ſuch a Diviſion the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Members may be conſidered. If I may gueſs by likely Circumſtances, I muſt needs ſay, I ſhould think it were the <hi>Gentry.</hi> Firſt, becauſe, <hi>Three</hi> of our chief <hi>Inns</hi> of Court Doctors, whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors are generally <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> are (as I hear) much addicted this way; ſo alſo are many of thoſe Preachers in whoſe <hi>Pariſhes</hi> the Gentry moſt inhabit, and to whoſe Churches or Lectures the Coaches chiefly throng. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> that which ſtrengthens me in theſe Conjectures as much as any thing elſe, is becauſe, I am told alſo, theſe kind of <hi>Sermons</hi> are managed with many Arguments, Inferences, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52535:12"/>too <hi>Subtile</hi> and <hi>Sublime</hi> for moſt of the <hi>Commonalty</hi> to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; but whether it be the one or the other, I think we need not much inquire, ſince there are good grounds to induce a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Man to believe there is no reaſon for the fearing of <hi>either;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, to that <hi>degree</hi> as to require all that Preaching, we meet with in that kind.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Gentry,</hi> I ſee not why they ſhould be queſtioned. I ſhall not ſay any thing, how many of them being concerned in the <hi>Old Church Lands,</hi> have thereby their <hi>ſecular intereſts</hi> to ſtrengthen their <hi>Religious Sentiments;</hi> for I believe them to proceed upon higher and <hi>better Principles.</hi> That which to me ſeems to be a kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſolvable tye, to hold them firmly where they are, is what I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of moſt Men in all Religions, who when they do firſt <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandingly</hi> believe ſuch or ſuch a way of Religion to be beſt for them to chuſe, thoſe former ſatisfactions which they may be ſuppoſed to have then received, do ſo keep them to it, as they ſeldom admit of any future thoughts to call it in queſtion; not caring to engage themſelves in any <hi>new Controverſies,</hi> in things wherein they judge that they have <hi>long ago</hi> been ſatisfied, but are rather improving themſelves (I ſpeak now of the moſt <hi>ſerious ſort</hi> of the <hi>Gentry</hi>) in thoſe pious practices which their Religion directs them to, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in divers of our Gentry are very Eminent. And this I take to be the true Natural Reaſon, why we find ſo few changing their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion after a good maturity in Years and Judgment, but thoſe whoſe deſigns leads them to do it either in <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> or <hi>Policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides all this, I look upon our <hi>Gentry</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of that <hi>Ingenuity</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> as that many of them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>the grounds</hi> upon which they are Proteſtants, as well as any of the <hi>Clergy</hi> can Teach them; ſo that I ſhould think theſe freſh and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeated arguings and preſſing them againſt the R. Catholick Religion, now uſed by our Church-Men, are rather a kind of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching</hi> them of <hi>weakneſs</hi> in their Profeſſion, then any neceſſary <hi>ſupport</hi> the Gentry ſtand in need of; Multiplyed <hi>cautions</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections being only needful for them that are <hi>weak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe <hi>others</hi> of the Gentry, and ſo alſo of the Commonalty, who careleſly take up their Religion, and are more relax in their Piety, they may be the <hi>leaſt feared</hi> of all. Thoſe ſtrict obſervances that are uſed in the R. Catholick Chappels, as alſo the <hi>Abſtinencies,</hi> ſolemn <hi>Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Penances</hi> that muſt be ſubmited to by ſuch as are of that Religion, will keep theſe Men more from it, then all the florid Sermons they can hear Preach againſt it. Nay, to ſpeak
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52535:12"/>a bold Truth, Perſons indifferently diſpoſed to the <hi>Mortifications Donations,</hi> and ſelf <hi>Denials</hi> which the <hi>Chriſtian inſtitution</hi> directs, and are withal told by their Conſciences that they muſt be of ſome Religion or other, have ſcarce any Church elſe ſo accommodated for them to take ſhelter in, as the <hi>Church of England;</hi> the <hi>Reins</hi> of whoſe <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and Caſtigation are left ſo looſe, as Men may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in injoy ſeveral of their ſenſual gratifications; yea, and be in a fair (or rather very foul) degree <hi>prophane</hi> too, without being called to any account, or fall under the cenſures of the Church for it; which neither in the R. Catholick Church, nor in the Diſſenters Churchs will be allowed them; wherefore there is no fear of them neither.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Commonalty</hi> which are indeed the greater Bulk of the People, may (I confeſs) come under ſome other Conſideration, as they are not ſo <hi>Learned</hi> as we may judge the Gentry to be; but then we muſt know that vaſt Numbers of them are <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> others are looſe and remiſs in their lives, both which ſtand upon the ſame points I have mentioned before; and as for thoſe who keeping to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are Serious and Sober in their Lives though not ſo intelligent as the Gentry are, it will appear to any that ſhall obſerve things as I have done; that the very <hi>Manner</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> of their Education, wrought in them ſo great an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to the R. Catholick Religion, as that though (it may be) they underſtand little of the Difference between the <hi>one Religion</hi> and the <hi>other;</hi> they yet carry on their oppoſition equally with thoſe who preſume themſelves the chief <hi>Maſters of Knowledge,</hi> and need no Preaching to increaſe their prejudice. And for thoſe of the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty that are more intelligent, I may ſay, they ſtand upon the ſame terms with the intelligent <hi>Gentry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the whole, therefore I muſt ſay, I ſee no kind of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> why ſo much of many Mens <hi>Sermons,</hi> which ought to be chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to promote <hi>Practical Duties</hi> and true <hi>Devotions,</hi> ſhould be ſpent this way againſt the R. Catholicks, unleſs it be to <hi>Prejudice</hi> the People againſt their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> which is the moſt natural effect it is like to have; for if the People be already thus prejudiced againſt his Religion, this ſuperabundant Preaching, and Haranguing againſt it in the Pulpit, is like to produce little betterfruit upon the Minds of ſuch Men, then the overcharging their <hi>Stomacks</hi> with meat doth upon their Bodies; though the meat of it ſelf be <hi>never ſo good,</hi> yet it moſt commonly begetteth more <hi>Crudities</hi> and ſower <hi>Belchings</hi> then good Nouriſhment, nor can I ſee any better event liklier to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from many of theſe <hi>Sermons</hi> then the raiſing an abundance of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52535:13"/>popular <hi>Talk, prejudice</hi> and diſſatisfactions againſt the <hi>King;</hi> for all People will be Diſcourſing of what they hear <hi>Preacht,</hi> eſpecially, when the Subject Preach'd upon, hath any relation to Perſons in a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Station, who they think and look upon to be chiefly <hi>pointed at</hi> in ſuch Sermons, and the higher theſe Perſons are in Dignity, whoſe Religion is thus <hi>levelled</hi> at, the more buſie will the People be in their <hi>Cenſures</hi> and <hi>Reflections:</hi> and how the King is like to be <hi>Honored</hi> by all this, I leave to all theſe Preachers to Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Preaching againſt the Kings Religion, muſt then be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the <hi>Loyalty</hi> as before deſcribed; when it is ſo managed as to beget in Men thoſe <hi>Jealouſies, Cenſures,</hi> and <hi>Suſpicions</hi> as ſhall in any wiſe <hi>alienate their Hearts and Affections</hi> from him, and their ſervice of him: When I conſider this well, and call to mind what a kind of influence irreſiſtable I have obſerved in ſuch kind of Preaching (where the Kings Religion, or the Government is any wiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned) to have had on the minds of Men. I cannot but pray our Doctors to conſider well with themſelves, what prejudice they may do <hi>the King</hi> before they are aware; and perhaps repent when it is too late: As thoſe <hi>London</hi> Preachers did, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1641. 1642. who then extravagantly Preacht againſt the <hi>Liturgy, Biſhops</hi> and their <hi>Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> as our Church-Men have lately done againſt the R. Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and I pray what followed but that fatal <hi>War,</hi> whoſe ſad effects we all to this day deplore.</p>
            <p>The prejudices raiſed in Perſons upon the account of <hi>difference</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are hardly poſſible to be related; let me inſtance in Proteſtants only where the diſtance is not ſo great (even according to the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> own acknowledgments) as it is between the R. Catholicks and the Proteſtants; and yet <hi>how</hi> have they carryed it one towards another (as they have gotten <hi>power</hi> ſucceſſively into their hands) where let the Church of <hi>England</hi> come in for as great an Example as any of the reſt; have not they thought ſo hardly of their Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Brethren in the Miniſtry, that could not comply with them in things which themſelves ſay are but <hi>indifferent,</hi> as that thoſe that refuſed to wear a <hi>Surplice,</hi> muſt be kept ſo poor as not to be able to buy a <hi>Shirt.</hi> Ay! I might go yet a great deal higher, did not the prejudice of many (and thoſe ſome of them zealous enough for the Church of <hi>England</hi>) influence them ſo far as to conceive that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Majeſty was of the R. Catholick Religion, he was not fit to be their King?</p>
            <p>Church-Men may think of theſe things as they pleaſe, but I am ſure our wiſeſt ſort of <hi>States Men</hi> were of another Opinion, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52535:13"/>pears by what was enacted in the Parliament, <hi>Anno.</hi> 13. <hi>Car.</hi> 2d. who ſenſible of the ill effects ſuch prejudices may produce, where the King is the object of them, made a Law, <hi>That whoſoever ſhould publiſh, or affirm the King</hi> to be an <hi>Heritick</hi> or a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or that he <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to introduce Popery,</hi> they ſhould be diſinabled to hold any Office or promotion <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Civil;</hi> making equal proviſion againſt either <hi>Catholicks</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that might offend this way. And the reaſon of this may be collected from the words of the <hi>Act</hi> it ſelf, which was becauſe they knew the repreſenting of the Religion of a <hi>King,</hi> in a way of odium to the People, was a thing tending to excite them to the hatred or diſlike of his Perſon and Government.</p>
            <p>Among other things I hear of as to this <hi>Preaching,</hi> there is one diſlikes me <hi>Exceedingly;</hi> as having in it the moſt potent influence of any thing I know tending to the ſetting of the People in oppoſition to the King, and that is thoſe Sermons, eſpecially, that intimate to them as if a time of <hi>PERSEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION</hi> were coming on, and the Obligation that lies upon all Perſons to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> whatſoever Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they meet with rather than to renounce any part of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. A <hi>Doctrine</hi> of excellent goodneſs in it ſelf, but I ſuppoſe now much <hi>miſtimed,</hi> unleſs we fear that <hi>Millions</hi> of Jews will invade us, and ſet up the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Sacrifices again, for I know not from whence Perſecution can otherwiſe come; if his Majeſties Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as he deſires) be turned into <hi>an eſtabliſh'd Law,</hi> which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, none but the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will endeavour to hinder.</p>
            <p>While ſome Conſidering Men think with themſelves, how little this of Doctrine they have heard Preacht upon for <hi>twenty years</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and now to be taken up ſince the King is come to the Crown, and made the Common <hi>Theam</hi> of the Pulpit, they know not how to interpret it, otherwiſe than that the <hi>Preachers</hi> would have the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>believe</hi> that their Religion is like to be <hi>denyed</hi> them; and if they will ſtand to it, they muſt expect <hi>to Suffer,</hi> which that they may the better do, it is neceſſary that they learn before hand how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves under ſuch Providences.</p>
            <p>And here again, it would make a Man <hi>Smile</hi> to ſee how the World turns round; I well remember, that when the Diſſenting Miniſters were firſt diſplaced at St. <hi>Bartholomews,</hi> 1662. Divers of them took their leave of their People the <hi>Sunday</hi> before in ſome <hi>Farewel Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> divers of which were Printed (by a good token that ſome of my acquaintance were ſoundly Puniſhed for <hi>Printing</hi> them.) In theſe Sermons ſuch Texts were choſen as from a <hi>Moral</hi> Prognoſtication they then made from the <hi>Conventicle Act,</hi> they thought fitteſt to induce
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52535:14"/>the People of a <hi>Patient Bearing</hi> of what was coming upon them; I ſhall name only that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. about taking <hi>joyfully the ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Goods,</hi> which was pertinent to the manner of their Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings ſince by that Act, all their Moveables lay liable to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>The ſame courſe is now taking by Divers Church of <hi>England Doctors,</hi> they have their particular Texts alſo fitted to what their <hi>Opinions</hi> are of the Times. One Preaches upon taking up the <hi>Croſs,</hi> as if a new Perſecution were indeed coming on. Another calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us (by his Text) <hi>to contend earneſtly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> as if a <hi>new Creed</hi> were to be immediately introduced. A third forewarns us of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, and this is applyed to the R. Catholick Religion; I mention theſe but as <hi>Specimens</hi> by which we may judge of the reſt, but here they would do well <hi>to take notice</hi> what ſome Men ſay of themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> that they do the ſame things which they before condemned in others, and for which they cauſed them to be <hi>puniſhed,</hi> which is ſo much the worſe in them than in the <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> for the latter had ſome ſhadow of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Preach as they did, when they ſaw <hi>a ſharp Law</hi> newly made againſt them; but for the Doctors of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to Preach thus, who have all the <hi>Laws on their ſide,</hi> and the Kings <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to protect them,</hi> for them to do this, and no other ground to proceed upon but their <hi>Miſbelieving</hi> the <hi>Kings Word;</hi> what elſe is it but a <hi>Diſingenious</hi> Diſloyalty, and that of the higheſt kind? Or what would they have the People think under all theſe things? And how can they do otherwiſe than produce moſt deſperate Jealouſies. The fatal Conſequences whereof, and the Reſentments that a Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Breaſt cannot but have of ſuch Treatment. I ſhall refer to the Judgment of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt to be informed of; who in his Meditations, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. Touching the jealouſies raiſed againſt him, who hath theſe Words: <hi>The worſt effects of an open Hoſtility come ſhort of theſe deſignes,</hi> this was the opinion he had of the Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch kind of dealing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, much what of the ſame Nature, and alſo to the Effect, is that way of Preaching when Men exert the utmoſt of their <hi>skill to Wyer-draw out of Texts</hi> ſuch thing againſts <hi>that Religion,</hi> thoſe Texts in their <hi>prime</hi> aſpects and genuine ſence to have little of any ſuch things in them. This can ſhew nothing elſe but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intention to the management of this oppoſition; this, an eminent Perſon who I care not to name hath lately done, when Preaching upon <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 47.5. God is gone <hi>up with a Shout,</hi> &amp;c. takes occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52535:14"/>on from thence to argue againſt the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> and the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick notion of the <hi>real preſence</hi> (as an ingenuous Perſon who in Print <hi>animadverted</hi> on the Sermon, hath obſerved) what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ground he may have for the <hi>firſt,</hi> becauſe, the Text ſpeaks of an Eminent Exaltation of God, as he had ſhewn his Power and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Church in thoſe daies, and from whence thoſe Believers might in ſome meaſure conclude the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Kingdom,</hi> I will not diſpute: Though I believe our Doctors do not think this Supream Dignity of <hi>Chriſt</hi> excluſive to the Supremacy of <hi>Arch-Biſhops or Biſhops in</hi> England, for then they would deſtroy their own Hierarchie; only they would have no one that ſhould be univerſal, but keep the <hi>Principality</hi> to themſelves. I ſay, whatever ground he had for the <hi>firſt,</hi> the other was drawn out of it no other wiſe than by Head and Shoulders, for there is not the leaſt ſemblance of any ſuch thing in the Text.</p>
            <p>Another I have met with, and that is, of a certain Perſon who finds Arguments from a Text before <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood, againſt ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Practices, he Preacht upon thoſe words: And <hi>Enoch walked with God,</hi> and becauſe it was ſaid of him that he begat Sons and Daughters (the <hi>Dostor</hi> for that was the degree under which the Preacher ſtood) applyed it to rebuke the R. Clergies abſtinence from Marriage; but I think it had been better ſpared, becauſe, the R. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church Men, if I underſtand them aright, do not decline Marriage, for that they hold it inconſiſtent with Purity and Piety, but are guided rather by that <hi>Maxim</hi> of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>No Man that Warreth entangleth himſelf with the affairs of this Life;</hi> and though we affect not their inforced abſtinence that way, yet, certainly the freer any Man is from the care of <hi>providing</hi> for a Wife and Children, the more he is at Liberty for the <hi>Miniſterial</hi> Function. That which I would ſay, is, that all ſuch diſtorted Applications of Texts ſeem to me to be more of a kind of <hi>Peeviſhneſs,</hi> than intended for <hi>Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> for it ſtates not the Caſe fairly, unleſs the R. Catholick Doctors had declared themſelves in the ſame Manner, ſo that I know not what all theſe odd Applications of things mean, unleſs it be for fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the People with matter for their tongues to talk of, and filling their minds with fears and jealouſies that ſomething is coming upon them more than in their own reaſon they can any wiſe apprehend.</p>
            <p>And what indeed, as I ſaid before, is like to be a more natural iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of ſuch <hi>Sermons,</hi> then to draw the Peoples thoughts into a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Muſings, and fill their Mouthes with as much diſcourſe, to know what all theſe things Mean, and where they will Center; for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52535:15"/>to come to plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> either they muſt think theſe <hi>Preachers</hi> to Preach very <hi>Impertinently,</hi> and as an exerciſe of Wit, when they ſee them thus fetch things <hi>about</hi> and <hi>about,</hi> that they may at every turn have a blow againſt the Catliolick Religion; or they muſt think them under ſome <hi>profound</hi> Diſcoveries of the Catholicks doing or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome ſtrange things, which no body elſe can find out or imagine. For ſurely (ſay the People among themſelves) our Miniſters would never thus lay about them if ſomething more than <hi>Ordinary</hi> were not in the Caſe. Oh! (ſaies one, ſoon after ſuch Sermons are ended) <hi>how notably did our</hi> Doctor <hi>pay off the</hi> Papiſts <hi>to Day.</hi> Ah! (ſaies a ſecond) <hi>and is he not a Man of rare Parts, that can find ſuch matter againſt them out of ſuch a Text, which I never underſtood before?</hi> Oh! (ſaies a third) <hi>they would not be ſo much upon this Subject, but they fear we ſhall be over-run with</hi> Popery; <hi>we little think</hi> (adds he) <hi>what Sad Times are a coming.</hi> Thus, and ten times degrees worſe, do the People <hi>Banter</hi> among themſelves, upon their hearing ſuch kind of Sermons. In the midſt of all this talk, let me (I pray) put in a word or two among the reſt, and ask according to the purport of my Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, how theſe things conſiſt with the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? and the <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> they have formerly urged againſt the Diſſenters? and whether they believe the People by all this talk are like to <hi>Honor their King,</hi> while they are ſuggeſted to believe that he is ſuffering ſuch <hi>hard times</hi> to come upon them as they are hinting at.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And which is as bad as bad can be, and as much againſt true <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty,</hi> if not <hi>Piety</hi> alſo, as any courſe that can be uſed; this is when they ſo order their expreſſions in theſe Preachings, as to turn any of the parts of that Religion into Redicule, or expoſe them in a way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Thoſe that know any thing very well, know, that this hath been a Common way taken up by the Church of <hi>England</hi> Divines, wherein they have not only many <hi>Maſters</hi> in the <hi>Art,</hi> but very Famous <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> alſo; that ſtudy to make a Merriment of that way of Religion, which hath been different from theirs: Witneſs the <hi>beloved Books</hi> of our old <hi>Friendly Debates,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Sherlocks</hi> knowledge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> wherein he ſo notably abuſes and derides the Notion of our Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Reformers in the Doctrines of our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with <hi>Chriſt, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Perſeverance,</hi> &amp;c. which were afterwards generally held by the Church of <hi>England</hi> Biſhops and Preachers until ſome few years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our laſt new <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity Act;</hi> ſome of which together with the friendly debate it ſelf, as alſo <hi>the deſigns</hi> of ſuch <hi>undertakings,</hi> may poſſibly before another year go about be re-debated in a new <hi>Friendly Debate</hi> like his own. But I muſt now proceed to my inſtance under
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52535:15"/>this head, as I have done before, wherein I ſhall bring only two. The firſt is, from a Sermon Printed, the other is from a Sermon Preacht, and that in the City by a Lecturer there, ſometime the laſt Spring.</p>
            <p>The Printed Sermon is that of Doctor <hi>Tenniſons,</hi> before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at an Aniverſary Meeting to Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate the Eminent Charity of the City Hoſpitals; I confeſs the Sermon was Preacht before his preſent Majeſty came to the Crown; however, I ſhall make uſe of it, firſt, becauſe, it is a <hi>Publick</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the <hi>Strain</hi> and <hi>Vain</hi> of theſe Mens Preaching againſt any way of Religion which themſelves oppoſe. 2. Becauſe, the Paſſage I am to take out of it, ſhews how ſharply they have rediculed upon the Kings Religion.</p>
            <p>To this grave Auditory he Preaches upon the Text, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 112.5. Where after he had handled all things very well, and ſutable to the occaſion of exciting Men prudently to give Alms, he falls upon ſcoffing the R. Catholick Charity, and eſpecially, touching the <hi>Scope</hi> and <hi>Event</hi> of it, which he moſt ſtrangely reprenſents. The beſt way will be to recite his own Words. <q>The <hi>Scope</hi> (ſaies he) they too often vainly aim at, is the bleſſing of a <hi>preſumed Saint</hi> who is ignorant of them; <hi>Security</hi> from the External force of evil Spirits by the Charms and Spells of Monkiſh Conjuration, (a ſort of Eccleſiaſtical Magick which theſe very Spirits invent and incourage.) Avoidance of thoſe Cauſeleſs <hi>Curſes</hi> and <hi>Anathamas,</hi> which are with terror denounced from their ſeven hill'd counterfeit <hi>Sinai;</hi> preſervation from, or deliverance out of the Imaginary Flames of Purgatory, blown on purpoſe by <hi>Jeſuitick</hi> Breath for the melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Treaſures of the Credulous People.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The <hi>Event</hi> is the Alienation of Alms from their proper uſes, the increaſe of Superſtition, and the maintaining of an Univerſal Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, for the <hi>pence</hi> of St. <hi>Peter</hi> conducted to the buying of ſuch a Yoak, as neither we nor our Fathers were able to bear.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The things we purchaſed conducive to thoſe ends, are the wares of dark Impoſtures, namely ſuch as theſe, <hi>viz. Shrines, Images, Lamps, Incenſe, Holy Water, Agnus, Dei's, Bleſſed Grains; Roſes, Peebles, Rings, Beads, Reliques, Pardons,</hi> &amp;c.</q> after all which he concludes with an <hi>Ironical</hi> Jeer.—The goodly Inventory of <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Church of <hi>England</hi> think theſe Expreſſions to become the Gravity of a Doctor, or be like the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>ſound</hi> Words in which <hi>Timothy</hi> was adviſed to Preach, or Words of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erneſs</hi> in which St.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52535:16"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> Preached to <hi>Feſtus,</hi> or meet to be ſpoken in the greateſt and moſt Honourable Audience of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or fit to agree with the Solemnity of a Divine Inſtitution, I muſt then bid fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to all reverence in their Religious Aſſemblies, ſuch ſtuff I might have expected in the Comedy called the <hi>Spaniſh Curate,</hi> written I think to abuſe the Catholicks, but never expected them in a Church of <hi>England</hi> Doctors Sermon.</p>
            <p>Theſe Paſſages are ſo Notorious, as that another Writer hath Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſome of them before my ſelf, which made me think once to have left them out; but then I found that either the Doctor or ſome body for him, had made Exceptions againſt the Writer for leaving out the Word <hi>[frequently,]</hi> while he repreſented him ſaying, That the <hi>Scope</hi> of their <hi>Charity</hi> did vainly Aim at the Bleſſing of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed <hi>Saint,</hi> &amp;c. Well! ſince he hath left it out, I have placed it in: but I know not what good it will do him, unleſs it be that he intends thereby to take ſhelter under the common Proverb: <hi>[Almoſt and hard by, ſaves many a Lie.]</hi> And ſo when his deſign is to render the R. Catholick Charity wholly Ridiculous, he would think to hide it by ſaying that <hi>[frequently or too often]</hi> they make thoſe vain Aims; but this will not ſerve his turn, ſince all the Charity they ſhew towards any poor Proteſtants is not capable of ſuch an Aim as he mentions, and therefore I muſt, never the leſs his complaining, affirm two things to be very ſoul in theſe Paſſages, <hi>viz.</hi> The Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his dealing, and the Scurrulity of his terms.</p>
            <p>There are I believe many hundred <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> who from their own experience of the R. Catholicks Charity towards them, will have occaſion to oppoſe him in ſaying that the <hi>Scope</hi> and <hi>Event</hi> of their Charity <hi>(too often aimed at)</hi> was to have them prayed out of Purgatory, or buy <hi>Lamps, Beads, Incenſe,</hi> &amp;c. Becauſe, the R. Catholicks in all the Charity they have beſtowed on <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> knew before-hand that thoſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> they Liberally reliev'd were never wont to make any ſuch purchaſes, or uſe any ſuch Prayers, and therefore could have none of thoſe ends in the doing of it. I have in my own knowledge this 50 years underſtood it to have been the ſtanding Characters of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholick Gentry to have been Exceeding Liberal in all the Eminent parts of Charity; <hi>ſuch as Relieving the Sick, giving Money freely to thoſe that have wanted Bread, Lending as freely to others that only came to Borrow, Cloathed ſuch as have been Naked, putting out the Children of many to be Apprentiees, whoſe Parents could not do it themſelves;</hi> all which have been ſo great towards <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as in divers places the Catholicks have been
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52535:16"/>eſteemed to have out done thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the ſame things, taking the like number in any County of the one as of the other, therefore this muſt needs be an Unrighteous Aſperſion.</p>
            <p>The ſcurrulity is ſuch as to find it in a Sermon, exceeds all I have met with, what kind of words hath he here pickt up? <hi>Monkiſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations, Jeſuitick Breath, the ſeven hill'd Counterfeit</hi> Sinai, <hi>the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inventory of Superſtition, Eccleſiaſtical Magick,</hi> &amp;c. he talks alſo of <hi>Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Charms,</hi> and <hi>Spells;</hi> but certainly all this Language muſt be minted in ſome infernal Cell among ſuch Spirits where <hi>God</hi> is ſeldom named, unleſs it be very vainly: I hope he did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his Sermon with the Prayer that many of them do, <hi>viz. That all theſe Words which we have heard with our outward Ears, may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted in our hearts;</hi> for I take him to be the happieſt Man that could firſt forget ſuch Words as theſe are, and be delivered from the ſnare of following his bad Example in getting a habit of ſuch ill Language.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only tell him again of another part of his Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that is, in his <hi>Inventorying</hi> (as he calls it) of the ſeveral things he names, without giving his Auditory an account of the R. Catholicks uſe of thoſe things (ſuppoſing they have ſo many things in uſe in their Religion as he ſpeaks of,) for this in honeſty he ought to have done, that ſo his Auditors might have judged whether they did not give as good a <hi>Rational</hi> for them, as the Church of <hi>England</hi> gives for her uſe of the <hi>Surplice,</hi> the <hi>Ring in Marriage, Prayers over the Dead,</hi> and repeating ſuch words as theſe in putting the body of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deceaſed Perſon into the Grave, as a part of their worſhip. <hi>For as much as it hath pleaſed Almighty God, to take to himſelf the Soul of our Brother,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We commit his Body to the Ground,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hope of Reſurrection to Eternal Life,</hi> when they often know not how they liv'd or dyed: I may mention alſo, together with theſe, their ſtanding up at reading the Goſpel in the <hi>Communion Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> and ſitting when the ſame Scripture is read in a ſecond Leſſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I am of Opinion the R. Catholick Doctors do give reaſons for what they do in their <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> as well as the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth of <hi>Hers,</hi> which he ought to have told People, if he had deſigned in a Chriſtian way to have to reprehended them; but his not doing this, and jumbling and jingling all of them together as he doth, is equally Unrighteous as it is Scurrulous, but let's go to the next.</p>
            <p>The other is a Sermon Preacht upon that Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.6. <hi>When ye faſt not as the Hypocrites,</hi> from whence the Preacher would needs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52535:17"/>have a fling againſt Catholicks keeping <hi>Lent</hi> (for it was in that time that the Sermon was Preacht (whereby a ſubtile way he had found out, he would have them guilty of the Hypocrifie here intended; becauſe, while they abſtain all that time from <hi>Fleſh,</hi> yet ſaid he, they make <hi>full Meals</hi> of other food. I never yet heard any Man twitted or told of his <hi>full Meals</hi> or <hi>great Eating,</hi> but it was either to deride him, or break a jeſt upon him: and ſo I look upon this to be, and by the ſmiling of ſome of the People (I was told of) that heard the Expreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, I ſuppoſe they thought ſo too.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall neither take upon me to juſtifie the Obſervation of <hi>Lent,</hi> nor the manner of Faſting uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet this I cannot but ſay, if what the Gentleman ſpeaks of, be Hypocriſie in them, what is it in the Church of <hi>England?</hi> who keep it as a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Faſt, but yet teach their People no abſtinence at all, but leave them to ſeed on all ſorts of <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and well pallated <hi>Sauces</hi> as often, and to as full meals as they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>That the Church of <hi>England</hi> keep <hi>Lent</hi> as a Religious Faſt, their Commiſſioners at the <hi>Savoy</hi> Meeting with the Non-conforming Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhall ſpeak for them, for when the Non-conformiſts oppoſed the keeping it a <hi>Religious Faſt,</hi> they anſwered them. <q>That their Faſting of 40 daies may be in imitation of our Saviour, for all that had been ſaid to the Contrary, for tho' we cannot arrive to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, abſtaining wholly from <hi>Meat</hi> ſo long, yet, we may faſt <hi>forty Daies</hi> together, either as <hi>Cornelius</hi> his Faſt till three of the Clock in the Afternoon, or St. <hi>Peters</hi> Faſt till Noon, or <hi>Daniels</hi> Faſt abſtaining from <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks</hi> of <hi>Delights;</hi> and thus far we imitate our Lord.</q> Thus they ſetled their <hi>Lent</hi> as a Religious <hi>Faſt,</hi> but by what has followed, it ſeems they never intended to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn their People any of thoſe abſtinencies in which that <hi>Faſt</hi> ought be kept, if it be kept at all; ſo that I may ask, where is the Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie now?</p>
            <p>But while I am thus Writing, I call to mind two great Reaſons (as they are eſteem'd) which I hear alledged in juſtification of their preſent Preachings. <hi>Firſt,</hi> they ſay all Miniſters are to declare to the People the <hi>whole Council of God,</hi> and by vertue of their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Office, they have a power of Preaching what they think moſt fit. <hi>Secondly,</hi> they tell us, that there are a great number of R. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Prieſts up and down the City, privately Alluring and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading the People to embrace that Religion, which tenders their Preaching againſt it at this time abſolutely <hi>Neceſſary.</hi> Unto both theſe I ſhall give a diſtinct anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52535:17"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall not diſpute their Power in Preaching upon what Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects they pleaſe, nor do I know ſo much as one Man that would deprive them of that Liberty; ſo that it be alwaies exerciſed and kept within the bounds of thoſe things, which the People may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly know are indeed the abſolute Counſel of God but in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſial matters, I know not how this can be; for the People muſt needs know that one part in all ſuch Sermons, muſt not be the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God</hi> but againſt it, for though both parties Preach upon that pretence, yet there is but one Truth, which hath alwaies made me think that Controverſies were not fit for <hi>Sermons,</hi> but rather <hi>Books</hi> or private <hi>Conferences;</hi> for while a controverſial point is handled in a Sermon, the hearer may ſtart ſome Objection in his thoughts, which it may be the Preacher never ſo much as toucheth at whereby the whole matter is left in doubt, which as often as it happens, ſuch hearers cannot receive thoſe things as <hi>the Counſel of God,</hi> though they ſhould really be ſo, and there all the labour that way is loſt.</p>
            <p>Again, it may be queſtioned that ſuppoſing thoſe Doctrines againſt which our Clergy Men are ſo frequently Preaching, ſhould not be the <hi>Councel of God;</hi> it may yet be conſidered, whether or no, it be according to the <hi>Councel</hi> of his will, they ſhould juſt <hi>at this</hi> time, above all others, ſhew their oppoſition to them, when they can hardly manage it without endangering the People from falling off from a very great Duty towards their King, in which we are ſure it is the counſel of God they ſhould in no wiſe be defective. It was the Councel of God that Circumciſion, an Ordinance which himſelf had made for the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, ſhould not be continued in the Chriſtian Church, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo Vehemently Preached againſt it to ſome Churches, as that he told them if they were circumciſed, Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing; yet, upon another Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he Circumciſed <hi>Timotheus</hi> at <hi>Leſtria.</hi> It is a weighty point, I leave it to our Doctors to conſider, how far the Councel of God is to be Preached with reſpect to the different Circumſtances both of Time and of different Caſes.</p>
            <p>Again, do not all Men know what great prophanneſs there is among Multitudes, of thoſe who profeſs themſelves Members only of <hi>their</hi> Sanctuary, ſome are great Drunkards, others as great Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, ſome common Swearers, and that alſo of thoſe horrible Oaths, or Expreſſions which ought not to be Named, and not a few moſt deſperate Whorers, too many alſo Sabbath Breakers, whereof divers to my knowledg come frequently to <hi>Church,</hi> and very often receive the <hi>Sacrament.</hi> Now I ſhould think there are no Councels of God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52535:18"/>more neceſſary to be Preach'd to ſuch Sinners than thoſe that ſhould convince them of the Evil of theſe deſperate Courſes, and ſet them right in their <hi>Morals,</hi> before their Heads are filled with Diſputations in the Controverſal parts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet, who but ſuch Men as theſe, after a Sermon Preach'd againſt the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, talk more of it than they. I hope the Church of <hi>England</hi> Doctors do not think, that the only Capital Sins in <hi>England,</hi> are the <hi>Worſhipping</hi> of God without <hi>their</hi> Liturgy and Ceremonies, as the Diſſenters do, or to be of the R. Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and yet many wiſe Men of my acquaintance, have been tempted to believe ſo, by the Curſory Sermons we have had this Twenty Years, wherein we have had Preaching againſt theſe two Ranks of the Chriſtian <hi>profeſſion,</hi> than can be heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginſt all thoſe groſs Impieties I have named.</p>
            <p>To the Second Objection, that ſuppoſes a Multitude of Perſons, in holy orders of the Catholick Religion, to be privately inticing the Proteſtant People to leave their Religion. I thus Anſwer, That whether this be true or no, I cannot tell; but if it be, then I ſay our Church of <hi>England.</hi> Prieſts, and Doctors, may be as buſie and careful, if they pleaſe, to Counter-work them, by the like private Conferences with <hi>their</hi> Pariſhoners, and by inquiring who have been with them upon any ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which no Body that I know of will be againſt, but greatly commend it, as a moſt excellent way to ſecure their People from the Dangers they fear them to be in, as to their being drawn to the R. Catholicks, and prevent much of that Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is now ſo much doubted to be conſiſtent with their Loyalty.</p>
            <p>I would ſuppoſe that every Paſtor ſhould know all of his own <hi>Flock;</hi> or if he doth not, or hath taken a bigger charge upon him, than himſelf can overlook, he ought in ſuch caſes to take in thoſe, that may aſſiſt him to hold up ſo good a Work, ſo much to the advantage of their Miniſtry, as ſuch a Knowledge of the particulars of their Flock would do; for every Soul is to be looked after, by thoſe that take the Charge thereof, and are well paid for it too. By this means they may come to know all that the Catholick <hi>Prieſts</hi> do, and apply proper and pertinent Diſcourſes to the particular Caſes of their People, as they find moſt needful, and thereby Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them in thoſe points, wherein they find them moſt Wavering, which indeed cannot be well known, but by ſuch private Conferences, and therefore much more profitable than Preaching at Randum, ſometimes againſt this point, and ſometimes againſt that, when they know not at what joint particularly any of the People Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and in ſo doing, they would not only Letter ſecure their People, but better teſtifie alſo their Honor of the King.</p>
            <p>To watch, is their Work, as well as to Preach, and they are denominated as much by the one as by the other. Watching of the Flock includes the Knowledge of all Individuals. I ſear it is not ſo with us, becauſe many of our <hi>Parochialiſts</hi> have gotten their Pariſhes ſo large, as to render this Knowledge, and the Execution of this part of their office impracticable, and perhaps ſome will plead their Inability from thence, of doing that I recommend to them; but I muſt anſwer, that that they go ill to work, that will juſtifie one Irregularly with another, and to make the King ſuffer for their diſorder.</p>
            <p>How they will approve of this Expedient, I now propoſe, I do not well know; but ſince the Catholick Religion is the Kings Religion, I am certain ſomething ought to be done by them, in a Prudential way, how to behave themſelves under the preſent Circumſtances, as they are in a different way of Religion from him, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than I, yet hear many of them have done, let the Religion be what it will, doth not the King's profeſſion of it, alter the Cale in no manner, as to our behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? When. <hi>John</hi> according to Gods command, had Executed Judgment upon <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:52535:18"/>by ordering her to be thrown out of a Window; he would not have her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy left to be expoſed to all Spectators, but orders her to be Buried upon this very reaſon, <hi>becauſe ſhe was a Kings Daughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Apoſtles planted the Chriſtian Religion firſt in the World, they ſetled moſt of their Churches under Princes, who were wholly Strangers to the Chriſtian Faith, and as things were repreſented to thoſe Princes, by what the Jews had done in putting our Saviour to Death, as one that had made Mutinies, by <hi>ſtirring up the People, Luke</hi> 23.3. thoſe Princes according to humane Pollicies, had little reaſon to receive any of thoſe who were his Followers; which I believe was one great Reaſon of their Perſecutions; and yet we find the Ap ſtles (fearing it may be that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, becauſe of that, and their groſs Idolatries might diſpiſe thoſe Princes) do as carefully injoyn them to keep their Loyalty, as to abſtain from their Idol Worſhip. St. <hi>Paul</hi> moſt earneſtly preſſeth them to give all due ſubjection, and St. <hi>Peter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to <hi>Honor them,</hi> and this while they were not ſo much as Believers of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, ſutable to what our Soviour had done before, by his own Example to the Jewiſh Magiſtracy, when he was condemned to Death by them: <hi>He opened not his Mouth: He anſwered them nothing,</hi> as three of the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> obſerve; he could not approve of what they did, yet would he not reproach them in the thing they were about, and by this <hi>paſſive obedience,</hi> gave Honor to thoſe that wickedly put him to Death.</p>
            <p>I do very much queſtion, whether the Preachers in the firſt Age of Chriſtianity, under the Pagan <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, did Preach againſt the Religion, and Worſhip of thoſe Princes; as our Divines now do againſt the Religion of <hi>Rome,</hi> by what I find upon Scripture record; it appears to me, that they did not, but had other ways, ſuch as Conferences, Epiſtolary Writings, to ſecure the People in the Chriſtian Faith. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> Preach'd in the midſt of <hi>Mars-Hill at ATHENS,</hi> among a Company of Heathen <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and common People; it is obſervable, how gently he touch'd upon their Idolatrous Religion: He told them indeed, that they <hi>were too Superſtitious,</hi> but he made not any <hi>Goodly Inventory</hi> of the <hi>particulars,</hi> as Doctor <hi>Teni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> did for the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> but falls preſently upon declaring to them the Doctrine of the <hi>only true God,</hi> and his Creating the World: His ſending of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> The <hi>Eternal Judgment,</hi> and <hi>the Reſurrection,</hi> chooſing rather to fix them in the Great Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and the Sutable Practices of a Holy Life, to which ſuch Doctrines would lead them, than to be <hi>Crying</hi> out againſt their <hi>Idolatries:</hi> as knowing if once they come to embrace the Chriſtian Doctrines, their Heatheniſh <hi>Worſhip</hi> would fall of its own accord.</p>
            <p>If after all this, nothing will prevail, but our Church-men will be ſtill Preaching in this way. I have one thing to ſay more, which is to wiſh them to follow the <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of thoſe Apoſtles, who when they wrote to the Churches againſt a Religion ſo groſs, as that of the Pagan <hi>Idolatry,</hi> did withal give the Chriſtians poſitive Commands, to keep up their Subjection and Honour to their Kings: The like would I have our Preachers do at all ſuch times, as they Preach againſt any part of the Kings <hi>Religion, viz.</hi> to teach the People at the very ſame time, in ſome ſpecial manner, how they ſhould preſerve in themſelves the Honour, and Loyalty they owe to his Perſon; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs their differing from him in their Religion. If they do not put in ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Caveats of this kind, as often as they Preach upon ſuch Subjects (which hitherto I cannot hear they have done) I muſt for my ſelf ſay they will hardly ever be able to vindicate the Loyalty they have ſo much boaſted of in the World.</p>
            <p>I have done with the Preaching, I would proceed now to ſay ſomething (tho but a little) about <hi>theirs</hi> and the <hi>Peoples</hi> Speaking; more eſpecially, their Speaking
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52535:19"/>againſt his Majeſties Proceedings by his <hi>Declaration,</hi> and the odd Carriages of them both in that concern.</p>
            <p>What the diſcourſes of the Church of <hi>England</hi> People have been, and ſtill are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Subject, I have mentioned already; I am not ſo in love with repeating ill <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages,</hi> as to name it over again. It is no wonder the People ſhould talk at the rate they have done, while they hear and ſee what has been ſaid and done by their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Clergy. The <hi>Declaration</hi> was no ſooner diſperſed about the Kingdom, but Doctor <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> Re-prints his Sermon, called, <hi>the Miſchief of Separation,</hi> Preacht be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Mayor of <hi>London</hi> againſt the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> Worſhip, in as ſharp a manner as his wonted <hi>Oratory</hi> uſeth to do towards thoſe he hath a mind to laſh; (of which he may hear more at another time.) What he intended by the new ſetting it out, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf beſt knows<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I inquire not after it, I ſhall only inform him that this Act of his is looked upon by many as a direct affront to the <hi>Declaration,</hi> as if he would have the People to believe that His Majeſty had tollerated a <hi>Miſchievous</hi> thing.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Oxford Clergy</hi> do as good as call it by the opprobrious <hi>Name</hi> of a <hi>Suſpected Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice,</hi> for when their <hi>Lioceſan</hi> moved them to make ſome publick Teſtimony (as a few others of their Church had done) of their thankful ſenſe of what the King had declared, touching their being protected in their preſent Station and Worſhip; they excuſe themſelves by making it one Reaſon of their refuſal, that by doing ſo they ſhould <hi>forfeit their Reputation with the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty of their Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and that it may tempt thoſe Perſons to diſguſt them for their raſh Compliance with ſuſpected Artifices.</hi> Language I ſhould have ſcarce expected from the greateſt <hi>Clown</hi> in the Country; however, I perceive they reſolved to ſpeak their thoughts <hi>Freely,</hi> by which we may a little know their Minds</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Preaching</hi> I ſpoke of before, the People were taught how to form their Jealouſies againſt the King, as that he would alter their Religion, and theſe Men now tell them the <hi>Declaration</hi> is the <hi>Artifice</hi> they ſuſpect for the bringing it about.</p>
            <p>If they ſay I ſtrain this too far, and put upon it a ſenſe they intend not, I muſt then pray them to <hi>explain</hi> their own ſenſe more fully, and tell us what it is that in that <hi>Expreſſion</hi> they do intend; for until they do, I cannot underſtand them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than I now <hi>Write,</hi> there being ſuch a near Relation between the Peoples Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing to the King, and the Declaration it ſelf from whence they take the occaſion, as none can hardly ſay, the one is a <hi>Suſpected Artifice,</hi> but they muſt ſay the other is ſo too.</p>
            <p>But there are other <hi>ſtrains</hi> not inferiour to this I have laſt named. They will not thank the King by an <hi>Addreſs,</hi> becauſe, forſooth it will make the Exerciſe of their Eſtabliſhed Religion to be Precarious: As if when a Father ſhall ſay to any <hi>Son</hi> at his coming to Age, SON! Care was taken upon the Marriage of your Mother to ſetle an Eſtate upon you, which now you ſhall injoy ſo far from any interuption from me as I promiſe to give you the beſt protection I can in your poſſeſſion of it. The Son ſhall ſay, Sir, I muſt not thank you for any thing of this, leaſt I make my Title to what I have too Precarious: I wiſh they come not at laſt to ſay, we muſt not thank Almighty God for the Spiritual Bleſſings he beſtows upon us by his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, ſince that Covenant was made and Eſtabliſhed with our fore Fathers long before we had a being, and that in a firmer manner than all our humane Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can pretend to be. I cannot believe otherwiſe but that all ſubordinate rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſtand bound (upon every ſignal Teſtimony of Special Favour they receive from their Superiors) to make their acknowledgements of thanks, whatſoever Obligation they may conceive their ſuperiors might have before-hand put themſelves under, while it was in their Power to have done otherwiſe with us if they had pleaſed; nor do I ſee any thing in all theſe Doctors Arguments, that is like to alter my Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52535:19"/>
Had all the People in <hi>England</hi> told me four or five years ago, that I ſhould have ſeen and heard ſuch things as theſe, and others I have lately met with from divers of our Church Men towards the King; I do <hi>profeſſedly</hi> declare; I ſhould never have believed them. I hear alſo they have Queſtion'd or Diſobey'd rather his Orders in diſpoſing of ſome <hi>Places</hi> which his Majeſty would fill up, or where he thinks it convenient to make an <hi>Alteration.</hi> Ay! is it come to this alreeady? will they thus <hi>diſpute</hi> it with their King? if they begin thus, I know not where they will make an end; as Men when once but of the way of their Duty, no body knows where they will <hi>Stop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one thing more in theſe <hi>Oxford</hi> Mens <hi>Reaſons,</hi> for their <hi>Non-Addreſſing</hi> with their thanks to the <hi>King,</hi> which I cannot paſs by without ſome Remark. They ſay, they do not offer thoſe Reaſons as the ſenſe of their own Minds only, but undertake to affirm them to be the Opinion alſo of the <hi>best part</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the Kingdom; by the <hi>beſt,</hi> I preſume they mean the <hi>greateſt</hi> part, but, how they came ſo ſoon to know each others Minds in ſo great a Kingdom as this, is unto many no ſmall won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: I hope they are not hatching another <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> for ſecuring the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as that which they ſo much exploded in one of the late Parliaments; if they are, much good may do them, I intend not to be of the <hi>Fraternity;</hi> but ſuppoſing them to have this <hi>intelligence</hi> one from another more then I am aware of. I may ſtill wonder how they undertake ſo far for the Nobility and Gentry as to know <hi>their</hi> thoughts ſo much in the caſe, while they ſeem to fear that <hi>thanking</hi> the King for his promiſed Favours, will forfeit their Reputation with <hi>them,</hi> as <hi>Men that had too raſhly complyed with ſuſpected Artifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think by the Carriage of many, both of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> towards the Kings Perſon, and his afairs in the Court and Country, I may reaſonably conclude they give them no grounds for ſuch a Conjecture. In my apprehenſion, therefore this looks too much like a <hi>Subſtile</hi> inſinuating their own diſlikes into thoſe that are in that honourable Station; that thereby they may be pre-ingaged againſt his Majeſties proceedings than any real ground they had to fear <hi>their</hi> diſpleaſure, if they ſhould have returned the Kings thanks for the aſſurance he hath given of his protecting and Supporting <hi>their Church.</hi> To ſay no worſe of the matter, it is no fair dealing towards perſons ſo much their betters, nor hath it ſo much as one ſpark of <hi>Loyalty</hi> in it towards the King.</p>
            <p>How the people ſhould avoid the being enſnared in their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> by ſuch bad Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples as theſe, I no waies apprehend, my fears (I muſt profeſs) are not a few, and I ſhall crave ſo much leave as to lay before them two or three Conſiderations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may ſee how much ſuch kind of Speeches and Diſcourſes as I ſpoke of before, carry in them of <hi>Diſloyalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> as they are directly oppoſite to that ſubjection we owe to the Kings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, they muſt ever be diſloyal; that they are ſo oppoſite is plain, becauſe, ſuch kind of Speaking is no better then reſiſtance, which is contrary to Subjects Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I pray obſerve, how the Duty of perſons who are alwaies in a State of Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (ſuch as Women and Servants) is ſet out in ſacred Writ towards their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and you will find it to be a State of ſilence. <hi>Let the Woman keep ſilence in all Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſervant alſo is ſtrictly warned <hi>not to anſwer again,</hi> but give obedience without diſputing his Maſters Commands. The diſtance is the ſame, between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Subjects,</hi> and I ſee no reaſon why the obligation ſhould not be the ſame in the <hi>Subject</hi> towards his <hi>Prince;</hi> as in a Servant to his Maſter, or a Wife to her Husband. It cannot but follow then, but that all theſe peremptory Diſcourſes, and Queſtionings of things about the <hi>Kings Proceedings,</hi> we ſo frequently meet with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52535:20"/>among the <hi>Body of the People,</hi> are much beſides their Duty as they are <hi>Subjects</hi> and great Tokens of <hi>Diſloyalty,</hi> in as much as they intimate their Minds and Hearts, to be in a way of Reſiſtance againſt them.</p>
            <p>The plain caſe of <hi>Obedience</hi> is given us by St. <hi>Peter. Submit your ſelves to every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Man, for the Lords Sake.</hi> And what is this Declaration, but the <hi>Kings Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,</hi> relating to the Execution of his Government. This General Rule of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is capable but of <hi>one</hi> Exception, that I could ever hear of, allowed in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and that is <hi>only</hi> when the thing ordained or commanded, appears to be <hi>againſt ſome Command of God,</hi> wherein <hi>God</hi> muſt always be <hi>obeyed</hi> before <hi>Man,</hi> but this Exception hath no <hi>Shadow</hi> of place <hi>here;</hi> for the <hi>Declaration</hi> hath no <hi>Command</hi> at all in it. It is only his Majeſties Prohibition of his Subordinate Officers, to ſuſpend their <hi>Execution</hi> of ſome puniſhments, which an hundred Years experience have made appear to be very hurtful to the publick Peace, and grievouſly oppreſſing to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, with promiſes of <hi>Liberty</hi> in Religion, for the <hi>promoting</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Property,</hi> for the main <hi>maintaining</hi> of <hi>Honesty.</hi> Now is any thing of this againſt a Command of God, that we ſhould refuſe to give Subjection to it?</p>
            <p>Had the <hi>King</hi> dealt by us, as we have dealt by him, and by one another, or had he required of us, to give <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to any thing in <hi>his</hi> Religion, that is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us, or impoſed upon us any new Oaths, or <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> to controveried propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, or any different ways of Religions, than what we now profeſs, ſomething might have been ſaid, to have juſtified our Diſſatisfaction: But for ſuch a Declaration as this is, which to every Man is but a <hi>Negative</hi> thing, to ſee Men riſe up againſt it with full Mouth, as if ſome thin horrible Evil were commanded in it, may become the Worlds wonder.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Speaking I have mentioned againſt his Majeſties Declaration muſt be very Guilty of Diſloyalty, becauſe it cannot be excuſed from a <hi>down-right diſhonouring him;</hi> what is a greater Diſhonor to an ordinary Man, than to have the Truth of his word or promiſe called in queſtion? how much more then to a <hi>King?</hi> How can it conſiſt with Honouring the King, to ſay, he either <hi>uſeth</hi> or <hi>indulgeth</hi> ſuſpected <hi>Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</hi> Or that he will do ſuch things as againſt which he hath declared? what are theſe Speeches then, but manifeſt Reproaches, tending only to alienate his peoples good opinion of him. I need ſay no more, but only recite another paſſage from King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, who had been ſerved in much what the ſame manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I can more willingly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>loſe my Crown, than my Credit</hi> — <hi>Thoſe foul and falſe Aſperſions</hi> (meaning the Scandals caſt upon him, that he would alter the Religion, and Government of the Kingdom) <hi>were ſecret Engines imployed againſt my Peoples love of me. That undermining their opinion and value of Perſon; mine and their Enemies might at once; blow up their Affections, and batter down their Loyalty.</hi> You have all this in the ſame 15. Chapter of his <hi>Meditations</hi> I quoted before, who from a very ſharp Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering he underwent by ſuch kind of doings, was beſt able to expreſs their <hi>deadly</hi> miſchievous conſequences, and do any of us pretend to Loyalty, that are ſtill doing the ſame things?</p>
            <p n="3">3. My Third Reaſon againſt all ſuch Diſcourſes, is drawn from the bad <hi>Quality</hi> of them, as they muſt come within the compaſs of Unchriſtian <hi>Cenſoriouſneſs,</hi> what the difference is between <hi>Curſing</hi> the King in our <hi>Bed-chamber,</hi> and cenſuring him in the open World; as to the foulneſs of each of theſe Speeches, I ſhall not now determine, but of this I am ſure, that <hi>Cenſoriouſneſs</hi> was ever made Criminal in the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Who art thou</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that judgeſt another mans Servant.</hi> I need ſay no more, but change the Word a little, and ask who art thou that <hi>Judgeſt</hi> the Lords <hi>Vicegerent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52535:20"/>
I expect it will be demanded here, how I make any ſuch Diſcourſes, or Preaching as I have named to be a <hi>Cenſuring the King?</hi> I anſwer, let but Church Men if they can, <hi>aſſign</hi> me any true <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Cenſoriouſneſs,</hi> whereby they can defend ſome of their own Sermons, and the peoples diſcourſes of them, from coming within the guilt of that <hi>Crime,</hi> and I will read what I have Written: I know <hi>Accademical</hi> Doctors may do ſtrange things, yet, I confeſs, I never heard them pretend to the working any <hi>Miracles</hi> in things Natural, but I muſt here ſuppoſe them to make a kind of <hi>Miracle</hi> in <hi>Mortality,</hi> if they can bring off themſelves, and their Loyalty fairly in this thing.</p>
            <p>Our plain way of underſtanding cenſoriouſneſs is this, we ſay it is nothing elſe <hi>but judging another Mans Words or Actions to be ill or evilly intended without apparent evidence; or to be otherwiſe intended than he hath made us believe.</hi> This is the common evil <hi>Cenſuring</hi> that is between Men towards each other of equal rank, that of inferiours cenſuring Superiours is made ſome what ſtricter; but I ſhall not take the advantage of that but paſs it by, becauſe if our <hi>Cenſuring</hi> the King be againſt the moſt ordinary <hi>Notion</hi> of it, we ſhall find it much worſe when we come to conſider it in a <hi>Notion</hi> that is higher; ſo that the preſent caſe I am upon will be this The <hi>King hath declared</hi> he will protect the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the way of their Worſhip, as it is now Eſtabliſhed; but divers of them Judge otherwiſe, looking upon his <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> as an <hi>Artifice</hi> to be ſuſpected as ſet on foot for another purpoſe, wholly againſt what they ought to believe of him, until they ſee apparent cauſe to Judge otherwiſe, either by acting or declaring himſelf different from what he now doth. The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion then is this, not to believe him is to cenſure him, and to cenſure him is to do evil againſt him, and every evil thing done againſt him is againſt our Loyalty.</p>
            <p>Now this conſuring muſt be ſo much the worſe in as much as while Men follow the conſequences of their own <hi>Reaſonings,</hi> they can ſee no grounds to believe that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion can receive any prejudice by any thing that can ariſe by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, without offering a kind of violence to their own reaſon. There are ſome perſons, who have given very great <hi>Reaſons</hi> againſt the likely-hood of the Catholicks Religion overthrowing or ſuppreſſing <hi>Proteſtantiſm,</hi> none of which I ſhall repeat; I ſhall only take notice of two other things, which I perceive to be much overlookt, which to me ſeem of very great force in giving Proteſtants a full aſſurance as to this Caſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, in that the <hi>Declaration</hi> indulgeth thoſe of the Proteſtant Religion, which are at the <hi>remoteſt</hi> diſtance from his <hi>Majeſties</hi> own <hi>Way;</hi> for ſo I muſt repute the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to be: as uſing no kind of <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in their Worſhip, nor ſo much as acknowledging the office of a Proteſtant <hi>Dioceſſan Biſhop,</hi> which is indeed the <hi>great</hi> Proteſtancy of Chriſtendom; whereas the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> rigidly impoſing the <hi>one,</hi> and ſtilly maintaining the <hi>other,</hi> together with their Symbolizing in both theſe reſpects with the R. Catholick Church and Worſhip. Yea, and in many Doctrines too of late, which the firſt Reformation oppoſed, have been thought to have been ſo near them, as the effecting of an union to the extirpation of the Diſſenters was the only thing feared, and this not without ground, while thoſe Diſſenters ſaw the Church of <hi>England</hi> upon the Death of his late Majeſty, to renew their proſecutions ſomewhat ſharper than before. But theſe fears are now abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly removed, which (truly) I muſt ſay could hardly have been done by any other means, than that which his <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath taken by his Declaration, which muſt be to all Men of underſtanding an evidence on his behalf, that he can have no deſigns againſt the Proteſtant intereſt, nevertheleſs the Church of <hi>England</hi> judging otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Admiſſion of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants in ſuch Multitudes as are come over hither, doth alſo confirm me in the ſame belief. They are a kind of <hi>Presbiterians,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52535:21"/>who becauſe they would not become Papiſts, are fled hither, where they have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of their Religion, but alſo very large Relief raiſed for their Neceſſities, and that too by his Majeſties own order. What greater Teſtimonies than theſe, can be given of his readineſs to ſupport <hi>Proteſtaniſme?</hi> And that <hi>He Acts</hi> in the <hi>higheſt degree</hi> of Sincerity to that Principle, upon which he Grounds his Declaration; <hi>viz.</hi> that Conſcience <hi>is not to be forced,</hi> from which we that are Proteſtants, cannot but repute our ſelves exceeding ſafe, and may conclude the Exerciſe of our Religion to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly continued to us, and that becauſe the Proteſtant Intereſt, from all theſe things is more and more ſtrengthened, and allowed to make its utmoſt advantage to maintain it ſelf in his Majeſties Kingdoms, all which may be ſo pleaded againſt the Cenſoriouſneſs I here condemn, as to make it appear to be every whit as <hi>irrational</hi> as it is <hi>diſloyalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The utmoſt that can be ſaid as to the benefit deſigned to the Catholicks by the <hi>Declaration,</hi> is only that his Majeſty would have thoſe of his own Religion enjoy the <hi>ſame Liberty</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> he hath given to the Proteſtant Diſſenters; and that they may be capable of ſerving him in Publique Employments as Proteſtants do: which, as it is all that is allowed them, ſo as (far as I perceive) it is as much as they deſire.</p>
            <p>To the Firſt, I would ask how can the King well do otherwiſe, according to that <hi>Divine Principle</hi> upon which he proceeds, and how can Proteſtants deny it that hold the ſame <hi>Principle</hi> with him, which I find none of them oppoſe, when the caſe is put home, and they have been pinch'd upon the point: for even our Church of <hi>England</hi> Divines themſelves chooſe rather to plead the obligation men are under to obey the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> whereby their Liturgy and Ceremonies are ſetled, than to inſiſt upon the denying this principle; and moſt generally juſtifie all their compulſions and <hi>penal</hi> inflictions from the Authority of our <hi>humane</hi> Laws; telling the people that the Diſſenters were not puniſhed for their diſobeying the Law; a fine way indeed to turn the odium of thoſe things upon the Parliament, which themſelves are aſhamed to own, and yet procured, and ſo much ſtruggle to have continued.</p>
            <p>To the Second, I would ask alſo, how we ſhall object againſt it, when we conſider that His Majeſty muſt needs in Equity have the ſame right to the ſervice of all his Subjects, as any Parents have to the Service of all their Children, or any men have to that which they call their Property. Tell me I pray, why we ſhould inſiſt upon holding our <hi>own property,</hi> and deny the King <hi>His?</hi> I would be glad to ſee our Doctors (who lately preach'd up <hi>Morality,</hi> ſo much in the <hi>Socinian</hi> way as if they would make the whole Inſtitution of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and of Chriſt's coming into the World to be only a ſubſervient thing to the Eſtabliſhment of the Primitive Moral Religion) to ſhew upon what principles of <hi>Moral</hi> right a King ſhall be denied the choice of thoſe that ſhall <hi>Serve</hi> him, more than a Noble Man the choice of his Steward, or the Maſter of a Family, his own Servants. As yet I would never underſtand that human Laws could ſupercede any <hi>Moral Right</hi> fixt in the <hi>Original</hi> Divine Conſtitution of things.</p>
            <p>I am no States Man, but judging naturally according to the ancient uſages of the Kingdom, the King is not to be impoſed upon in this particular, when a King dyeth, all publick Commiſſions formerly granted to his reſpective Officers become void: Nay, which is more, if a <hi>Parliament</hi> be then in being his Death <hi>diſſolves</hi> them, the reaſon whereof I could never hear to be <hi>Grounded</hi> upon any other bottom, but that a <hi>King</hi> was not to be <hi>impoſed</hi> upon, or bound up as to his <hi>Publick Miniſters</hi> and Officers, by any Act of his Predeceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52535:21"/>
There is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thing more I would take notice of at this time, which I have not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, to which I would ſay ſomething here, if I knew how to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it in; and this only what I obſerve from many of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who when they have little to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt that excellent Principle his Majeſty proceeds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in granting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for Gods free worſhip, nor the <hi>Moral</hi> Juſtice we owe him in chooſing his own Officers; they would fain pick a Quarrel with his <hi>Power,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe things ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> come to us in a <hi>Parliamentary way.</hi> I muſt confeſs the Power of a King is a thing ſo ſacred, and ſo ſtrongly <hi>Lodged</hi> and <hi>Seated</hi> in <hi>himſelf,</hi> as I have not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the leaſt to peep into it: Only what has been done this way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and univerſally approved of without being any wiſe called in queſtion, may (I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of without offence to any.</p>
            <p>That which I aim at in this, is only to note, how when ſomething of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was paſſed by the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, diſpenſing by his Proclamation with two diſtinct particulars enjoyned by Act of Parliament, as firmly as any of our Penal Laws about Religion can be, not a word was ever objected againſt it, as that it could not be done without a Parliament: The one was for <hi>prohibiting</hi> of <hi>Spices</hi> from being brought into <hi>England</hi> otherwiſe than in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bottoms, and the place of their <hi>growth.</hi> The other, about the form of <hi>Cart</hi> and <hi>Waggon</hi> Carriages for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Roads,</hi> in both which Statures his late Majeſty made a ſuſpention, and yet was never queſtioned in any <hi>Seſſion</hi> of that or future Parliaments, or by any of the Judges or Lawyers of the Kingdom, which to this day continues ſtill without any mans making the leaſt noiſe about it. Though no Parliament ever ſince gave that <hi>proceeding</hi> any confirmation, as being Judged to have been done <hi>firm</hi> enough by the <hi>power</hi> that made the alteration.</p>
            <p>This quarrel therefore is very unhandſome, as it denies this <hi>King</hi> that Power in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> which they allowed the former King in things <hi>civil,</hi> and is ſo much the worſe in this Caſe as it queſtions His Majeſties <hi>Prerogative in Eccleſiaſtical affairs,</hi> which the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Kingdom have ever acknowleged to him in a <hi>peculiar</hi> manner. In that <hi>very Act</hi> which was laſt made againſt Conventicles. A Clauſe was put in as a ſpecial proviſo, <hi>&amp;c. That nothing in that Act ſhall make void his Majeſties Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical affairs, but His Majeſty his Heirs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall injoy the ſame amply as himſelf or any of his predeceſſors have done nevertheleſs the ſaid Act.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly when this proviſo was made, the <hi>Parliament</hi> did acknowledg, that the <hi>King</hi> was not bound up by that <hi>Act;</hi> ſo as that he could not grant any Liberty againſt its injuctions, or ſuſpend the <hi>Execution</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, when it was wholly made, upon an Eccleſiaſtical Account: It muſt certainly be ſo alſo with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity Act,</hi> for his Prerogative is not leſs in that, becauſe, the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo is not made there, no nor to the <hi>Test</hi> about Capacitating Men for holding of publick Offices, ſince the matter of it relates chiefly to propoſitions that concern mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all Men in the World, a Man would think our Clergy Men ſhould forbear ſo much as to have the leaſt thought of Queſtioning His Majeſties Power, touching what he has done by His <hi>Declaration,</hi> when as <hi>Praying</hi> for him in their <hi>Pulpits,</hi> they conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent him to God, <hi>as being over all Perſons, and in all Cauſes, as well Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52535:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>as Civil, Supream Governor and Moderator:</hi> For <hi>them</hi> therefore upon this <hi>ſmall</hi> and <hi>firſt inſtance</hi> of his Moderatorſhip, to call in queſtion <hi>this</hi> his <hi>Supremacy,</hi> either by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſpeaking againſt what he hath done, muſt give the People very ſtrange Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, for while they do ſo, what will the giving theſe <hi>Titles</hi> to Him be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on otherwiſe, but as Hypocriſie towards God, or a kind of <hi>Mock-Complement</hi> to the Kings Supremacy; let them therefore either acknowledg the <hi>Power</hi> he hath exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or elſe I know not how they will be able <hi>ſincerely</hi> to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to their own <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are divers other things I had thought to have added to theſe Diſcourſes, but I fear what is writen already, is more than many Mens leiſure will allow them to read: therefore I ſhall now forbear going any further, and rather becauſe it is like I may meet with ſome anſwerers, or at leaſt ſome better opportunity than I have at preſent; which may draw them forth, until which time I ſhall bid my Reader heartily Farewel.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52535:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
